<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "cloudstack.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>

<!-- Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
    or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
    distributed with this work for additional information
    regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
    to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
    "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
    with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
    
    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
    
    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
    software distributed under the License is distributed on an
    "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
    KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
    specific language governing permissions and limitations
    under the License.
-->

<section id="about-hosts">
    <title>About Hosts</title>
    <para>A host is a single computer. Hosts provide the computing resources that run the guest virtual machines. Each host has hypervisor software installed on it to manage the guest VMs. For example, a Linux KVM-enabled server, a Citrix XenServer server, and an ESXi server are hosts.</para>
    <para>The host is the smallest organizational unit within a &PRODUCT; deployment. Hosts are contained within clusters, clusters are contained within pods, and pods are contained within zones.</para>
    <para>Hosts in a &PRODUCT; deployment:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>Provide the CPU, memory, storage, and networking resources needed to host the virtual
        machines</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Interconnect using a high bandwidth TCP/IP network and connect to the Internet</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>May reside in multiple data centers across different geographic locations</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>May have different capacities (different CPU speeds, different amounts of RAM, etc.), although the hosts within a cluster must all be homogeneous</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>Additional hosts can be added at any time to provide more capacity for guest VMs.</para>
    <para>&PRODUCT; automatically detects the amount of CPU and memory resources provided by the Hosts.</para>
    <para>Hosts are not visible to the end user. An end user cannot determine which host their guest has been assigned to.</para>
    <para>For a host to function in &PRODUCT;, you must do the following:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>Install hypervisor software on the host</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Assign an IP address to the host</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Ensure the host is connected to the &PRODUCT; Management Server</para></listitem>        
    </itemizedlist>
</section>
