<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "cloudstack.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>

<!-- Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
    or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
    distributed with this work for additional information
    regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
    to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
    "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
    with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
    
    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
    
    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
    software distributed under the License is distributed on an
    "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
    KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
    specific language governing permissions and limitations
    under the License.
-->
<section id="accounts-users-domains">
    <title>Accounts, Users, and Domains</title>
    <formalpara>
        <title>Accounts</title>
        <para>An account typically represents a customer of the service provider or a department in a large organization. Multiple users can exist in an account.</para>
    </formalpara>
    <formalpara>
        <title>Domains</title>
        <para>Accounts are grouped by domains. Domains usually contain multiple accounts that have some logical relationship to each other and a set of delegated administrators with some authority over the domain and its subdomains. For example, a service provider with several resellers could create a domain for each reseller.</para>
    </formalpara>      
    <para>For each account created, the Cloud installation creates three different types of user accounts: root administrator, domain administrator, and user.</para>
    <formalpara>
        <title>Users</title>
        <para>Users are like aliases in the account. Users in the same account are not isolated from each other, but they are isolated from users in other accounts. Most installations need not surface the notion of users; they just have one user per account. The same user cannot belong to multiple accounts.</para>
    </formalpara>
    <para>Username is unique in a domain across accounts in that domain. The same username can exist in other domains, including sub-domains. Domain name can repeat only if the full pathname from root is unique. For example, you can create  root/d1, as well as root/foo/d1, and root/sales/d1.</para>
    <para>Administrators are accounts with special privileges in the system. There may be multiple administrators in the system. Administrators can create or delete other administrators, and change the password for any user in the system.</para>   
    <formalpara>
        <title>Domain Administrators</title>
        <para>Domain administrators can perform administrative operations for users who belong to that domain. Domain administrators do not have visibility into physical servers or other domains.</para>
    </formalpara>
    <formalpara>
        <title>Root Administrator</title>
        <para>Root administrators have complete access to the system, including managing templates, service offerings, customer care administrators, and domains</para>
    </formalpara>
    <formalpara>
        <title>Resource Ownership</title>
        <para>Resources belong to the account, not individual users in that account. For example,
            billing, resource limits, and so on are maintained by the account, not the users. A user
            can operate on any resource in the account provided the user has privileges for that
            operation. The privileges are determined by the role. A root administrator can change
            the ownership of any virtual machine from one account to any other account by using the
            assignVirtualMachine API. A domain or sub-domain administrator can do the same for VMs
            within the domain from one account to any other account in the domain or any of its
            sub-domains.</para>
    </formalpara>
    <section id="dedicated-host-cluster-pod">
        <title>Dedicating Resources to Accounts and Domains</title>
        <para>The root administrator can dedicate resources to a specific domain or account
            that needs private infrastructure for additional security or performance guarantees.
            A zone, pod, cluster, or host can be reserved by the root administrator for a specific domain or account.
            Only users in that domain or its subdomain may use the infrastructure.
            For example, only users in a given domain can create guests in a zone dedicated to that domain.</para>
        <para>There are several types of dedication available:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Explicit dedication. A zone, pod, cluster, or host is dedicated to an account or
                    domain by the root administrator during initial deployment and
                    configuration.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>Strict implicit dedication. A host will not be shared across multiple accounts. For example,
                strict implicit dedication is useful for deployment of certain types of
                applications, such as desktops, where no host can be shared
                between different accounts without violating the desktop software's terms of license.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>Preferred implicit dedication. The VM will be deployed in dedicated infrastructure if
                possible. Otherwise, the VM can be deployed in shared
                infrastructure.</para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <section id="dedication-how-to">
            <title>How to Dedicate a Zone, Cluster, Pod, or Host to an Account or Domain</title>
            <para>For explicit dedication: When deploying a new zone, pod, cluster, or host, the
                root administrator can click the Dedicated checkbox, then choose a domain or account
                to own the resource.</para>
            <para>To explicitly dedicate an existing zone, pod, cluster, or host: log in as the root admin,
                find the resource in the UI, and click the Dedicate button. <inlinemediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="./images/dedicate-resource-button.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <textobject>
                        <phrase>dedicate-resource-button.png: button to dedicate a zone, pod, cluster, or host</phrase>
                    </textobject>
                </inlinemediaobject></para>
            <para>For implicit dedication: The administrator creates a compute service offering and
                in the Deployment Planner field, chooses ImplicitDedicationPlanner. Then in Planner
                Mode, the administrator specifies either Strict or Preferred, depending on whether
                it is permissible to allow some use of shared resources when dedicated resources are
                not available. Whenever a user creates a VM based on this service offering, it is
                allocated on one of the dedicated hosts.</para>
        </section>
        <section id="using-dedication-how-to">
            <title>How to Use Dedicated Hosts</title>
            <para>To use an explicitly dedicated host, use the explicit-dedicated type of affinity
                group (see <xref linkend="affinity-groups"/>). For example, when creating a new VM,
                an end user can choose to place it on dedicated infrastructure. This operation will
                succeed only if some infrastructure has already been assigned as dedicated to the
                user's account or domain.</para>
        </section>
        <section id="dedicated-infrastructure-behavior">
            <title>Behavior of Dedicated Hosts, Clusters, Pods, and Zones</title>
            <para>The administrator can live migrate VMs away from dedicated hosts if desired, whether the destination
                is a host reserved for a different account/domain or a host that is shared (not dedicated to any particular account or domain).
                &PRODUCT; will generate an alert, but the operation is allowed.</para>
            <para>Dedicated hosts can be used in conjunction with host tags. If both a host tag and dedication are requested,
                the VM will be placed only on a host that meets both requirements. If there is no dedicated resource available
                to that user that also has the host tag requested by the user, then the VM will not deploy.</para>
            <para>If you delete an account or domain, any hosts, clusters, pods, and zones that were
                dedicated to it are freed up. They will now be available to be shared by any account
                or domain, or the administrator may choose to re-dedicate them to a different
                account or domain.</para>
            <para>System VMs and virtual routers affect the behavior of host dedication.
                System VMs and virtual routers are owned by the &PRODUCT; system account,
                and they can be deployed on any host. They do not adhere to explicit dedication.
                The presence of system vms and virtual routers on a host makes it unsuitable for strict implicit dedication.
                The host can not be used for strict implicit dedication,
                because the host already has VMs of a specific account (the default system account).
                However, a host with system VMs or virtual routers can be used
                for preferred implicit dedication.
            </para>
        </section>
    </section>
</section>
