<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "cloudstack.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<!-- Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
    or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
    distributed with this work for additional information
    regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
    to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
    "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
    with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
    software distributed under the License is distributed on an
    "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
    KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
    specific language governing permissions and limitations
    under the License.
-->
<section id="add-primary-storage">
  <title>Adding Primary Storage</title>
  <note>
    <para>Ensure that nothing stored on the server. Adding the server to CloudStack will destroy any
      existing data.</para>
  </note>
  <para>When you create a new zone, the first primary storage is added as part of that procedure.
    You can add primary storage servers at any time, such as when adding a new cluster or adding
    more servers to an existing cluster.</para>
  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Log in to the &PRODUCT; UI.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>In the left navigation, choose Infrastructure. In Zones, click View More, then click the
        zone in which you want to add the primary storage.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Click the Compute tab.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>In the Primary Storage node of the diagram, click View All.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Click Add Primary Storage.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Provide the following information in the dialog. The information required varies
        depending on your choice in Protocol.</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Pod. The pod for the storage device.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Cluster. The cluster for the storage device.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Name. The name of the storage device</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Protocol. For XenServer, choose either NFS, iSCSI, or PreSetup. For KVM, choose NFS
            or SharedMountPoint. For vSphere choose either VMFS (iSCSI or FiberChannel) or
            NFS</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Server (for NFS, iSCSI, or PreSetup). The IP address or DNS name of the storage
            device</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Server (for VMFS). The IP address or DNS name of the vCenter server.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Path (for NFS). In NFS this is the exported path from the server.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Path (for VMFS). In vSphere this is a combination of the datacenter name and the
            datastore name. The format is "/" datacenter name "/" datastore name. For example,
            "/cloud.dc.VM/cluster1datastore".</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Path (for SharedMountPoint). With KVM this is the path on each host that is where
            this primary storage is mounted. For example, "/mnt/primary".</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>SR Name-Label (for PreSetup). Enter the name-label of the SR that has been set up
            outside &PRODUCT;.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Target IQN (for iSCSI). In iSCSI this is the IQN of the target. For example,
            iqn.1986-03.com.sun:02:01ec9bb549-1271378984</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Lun # (for iSCSI). In iSCSI this is the LUN number. For example, 3.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Tags (optional). The comma-separated list of tags for this storage device. It should
            be an equivalent set or superset of the tags on your disk offerings</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>The tag sets on primary storage across clusters in a Zone must be identical. For
        example, if cluster A provides primary storage that has tags T1 and T2, all other clusters
        in the Zone must also provide primary storage that has tags T1 and T2.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Click OK.</para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
</section>
