<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "cloudstack.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>

<!-- Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
 or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
 distributed with this work for additional information
 regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
 to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
 "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
 with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
 
   http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
 
 Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
 software distributed under the License is distributed on an
 "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
 KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
 specific language governing permissions and limitations
 under the License.
-->
<section id="add-password-management-to-templates">
  <title>Adding Password Management to Your Templates</title>
  <para>&PRODUCT; provides an optional password reset feature that allows users to set a temporary
    admin or root password as well as reset the existing admin or root password from the &PRODUCT;
    UI.</para>
  <para>To enable the Reset Password feature, you will need to download an additional script to
    patch your template. When you later upload the template into &PRODUCT;, you can specify whether
    reset admin/root password feature should be enabled for this template.</para>
  <para>The password management feature works always resets the account password on instance boot.
    The script does an HTTP call to the virtual router to retrieve the account password that should
    be set. As long as the virtual router is accessible the guest will have access to the account
    password that should be used. When the user requests a password reset the management server
    generates and sends a new password to the virtual router for the account. Thus an instance
    reboot is necessary to effect any password changes.</para>
  <para>If the script is unable to contact the virtual router during instance boot it will not set
    the password but boot will continue normally.</para>
  <xi:include href="linux-installation.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
  <xi:include href="windows-installation.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
</section>
