<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "file:///C:/Program%20Files%20(x86)/Publican/DocBook_DTD/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "cloudstack.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<section id="add-load-balancer-rule">
	<title>Adding a Load Balancer Rule</title>
	<orderedlist>
		<listitem><para>Log in to the CloudPlatform UI as an administrator or end user. </para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>In the left navigation, choose Network.</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>Click the name of the network where you want to load balance the traffic.</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>Click View IP Addresses.</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>Click the IP address for which you want to create the rule, then click the Configuration tab.</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>In the Load Balancing node of the diagram, click View All.</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>Fill in the following:</para>		
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para>Name. A name for the load balancer rule.</para></listitem>			
			<listitem><para>Public Port. The port receiving incoming traffic to be balanced.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Private Port. The port that the VMs will use to receive the traffic.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Algorithm. Choose the load balancing algorithm you want CloudPlatform to use. CloudPlatform supports a variety of well-known algorithms. If you are not familiar with these choices, you will find plenty of information about them on the Internet.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Stickiness. (Optional) Click Configure and choose the algorithm for the stickiness policy. See Sticky Session Policies for Load Balancer Rules.</para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist></listitem>	
		<listitem><para>Click Add VMs, then select two or more VMs that will divide the load of incoming traffic, and click Apply.</para>
		<para>The new load balancer rule appears in the list. You can repeat these steps to add more load balancer rules for this IP address.</para>
		</listitem>	
	</orderedlist>
</section>
