<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "cloudstack.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<!-- Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
  or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
  distributed with this work for additional information
  regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
  to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
  "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
  with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
  http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
  software distributed under the License is distributed on an
  "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
  KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
  specific language governing permissions and limitations
  under the License.
-->
<section id="added-API-commands-4.2">
  <title>Added API Commands in 4.2</title>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>addIpToNic </para>
      <para>Adds an IP address to the NIC from the guest subnet. The request parameters are: nicid,
        ipaddress.</para>
      <para>The response parameters are: nicid, ipaddress, networkid </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>removeIpFromNic</para>
      <para> Removes the reserved IP for the NIC. The request parameters is: id.</para>
      <para>The response parameters are: true, false</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>listNics</para>
      <para>Lists the NIC details of the user VM; the API response also contains the Secondary IP
        addresses of the NIC. The request parameters are: nicid, virtualmachineid.</para>
      <para>The response parameters are: id, ipaddress, secondaryips, gateway, netmask, macaddr,
        broadcasturi, isolationuri, isdefault,</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>deleteAlerts </para>
      <para>Deletes the specified alerts. The request parameters are: ids (allowed to pass one or
        more IDs separated by comma); type (string); olderthan (yyyy-mm-dd format).</para>
      <para>The response parameters are: true, false </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>archiveAlerts</para>
      <para>Archives the specified alerts. The request parameters are: ids (allowed to pass one or
        more IDs separated by comma); type (string); olderthan (yyyy-mm-dd format).</para>
      <para>The response parameters are: true, false </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>deleteEvents </para>
      <para>Deletes the specified events. The request parameters are: ids (allowed to pass one or
        more IDs separated by comma); type (string); olderthan (yyyy-mm-dd format).</para>
      <para>The response parameters are: true, false</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>archiveEvents</para>
      <para>Archives the specified events. The request parameters are: ids (allowed to pass one or
        more IDs separated by comma); type (string); olderthan (yyyy-mm-dd format).</para>
      <para>The response parameters are: true, false </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>createGlobalLoadBalancerRule</para>
      <para>Creates a GSLB rule. The request parameters are name (the name of the global load
        balancer rule); domain name ( the preferred domain name for the service); lb algorithm (the
        algorithm used to load balance the traffic across the zones); session persistence (source IP
        and HTTP cookie); account name; and domain Id.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>assignToGlobalLoadBalancerRule</para>
      <para>Assigns a load balancing rule or list of load balancing rules to GSLB. The request
        parameters are: id (the UUID of global load balancer rule); loadbalancerrulelist (the list
        load balancer rules that will be assigned to global load balancer rule. These are second
        tier load balancing rules created with createLoadBalancerRule API. Weight is optional, the
        default is 1).</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>removeFromGlobalLoadBalancerRule</para>
      <para>Removes a load balancer rule association with global load balancer rule. The request
        parameters are id (the UUID of global load balancer rule); loadbalancerrulelist (the list
        load balancer rules that will be assigned to global load balancer rule).</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>deleteGlobalLoadBalancerRule</para>
      <para>Deletes a global load balancer rule. The request parameters is: id (the unique ID of the
        global load balancer rule).</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>listGlobalLoadBalancerRule</para>
      <para>Lists load balancer rules.</para>
      <para>The request parameters are: account (lists resources by account. Use with the domainid
        parameter); domainid (lists only resources belonging to the domain specified); id (the
        unique ID of the global load balancer rule); isrecursive (defaults to false; but if true,
        lists all the resources from the parent specified by the domainid); keyword (lists by
        keyword); listall (if set to false, lists only resources belonging to the command's caller;
        if set to true, lists resources that the caller is authorized to see. Default value is
        false); page; pagesize; projectid (lists objects by project); regionid ; tags (lists
        resources by tags: key/value pairs). </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>updateGlobalLoadBalancerRule</para>
      <para>Updates global load balancer rules.</para>
      <para>The request parameters are: id (the unique ID of the global load balancer rule); account
        (lists resources by account. Use with the domainid parameter); description (the description
        of the load balancer rule); domainid (lists only resources belonging to the domain
        specified); gslblbmethod (the load balancer algorithm that is used to distributed traffic
        across the zones participating in global server load balancing, if not specified defaults to
        round robin); gslbstickysessionmethodname (the session sticky method; if not specified
        defaults to sourceip); isrecursive (defaults to false, but if true, lists all resources from
        the parent specified by the domainid till leaves); keyword (lists by keyword); listall (if
        set to false, list only those resources belonging to the command's caller; if set to true,
        lists resources that the caller is authorized to see. Default value is false); page;
        pagesize; projectid (lists objects by project); regionid; tags (lists resources by tags:
        key/value pairs)</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>createPortableIpRange</para>
      <para>Creates portable IP addresses in the portable public IP address pool.</para>
      <para>The request parameters are region id, start ip, end ip, netmask, gateway, and
        vlan.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>deletePortableIpRange</para>
      <para>Deletes portable IP addresses from the portable public IP address pool.</para>
      <para>The request parameters is portable ip address range id.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>listPortableIpRange</para>
      <para>Lists portable IP addresses in the portable public IP address pool associated with a
        Region.</para>
      <para>The request parameters are elastic ip id and region id.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>createVMSnapshot (create a virtual machine snapshot)</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>deleteVMSnapshot (delete a virtual machine snapshot)</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>listVMSnapshot (show a virtual machine snapshot)</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>revertToVMSnapshot (return a virtual machine to the state and data saved in a given
        snapshot)</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>createLBHealthCheckPolicy (creates a new health check policy for a load balancer rule;
        see <xref linkend="health-check"/>)</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>deleteLBHealthCheckPolicy (deletes an existing health check policy from a load balancer
        rule)</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>listLBHealthCheckPolicies (displays the health check policy for a load balancer
        rule)</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>createEgressFirewallRules (creates an egress firewall rule on the guest network; see
          <xref linkend="egress-firewall"/>)</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>deleteEgressFirewallRules (deletes a egress firewall rule on the guest network.)</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>listEgressFirewallRules (lists the egress firewall rules configured for a guest
        network.)</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>resetSSHKeyForVirtualMachine (Resets the SSHkey for virtual machine.)</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>addBaremetalHost (Adds a new host. Technically, this API command was present in v3.0.6,
        but its functionality was disabled. See <xref linkend="baremetal"/>)</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>addBaremetalDhcp (Adds a DHCP server for bare metal hosts)</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para> addBaremetalPxePingServer (Adds a PXE PING server for bare metal hosts)</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para> addBaremetalPxeKickStartServer (Adds a PXE server for bare metal hosts)</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para> listBaremetalDhcp (Shows the DHCP servers currently defined for bare metal
        hosts)</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para> listBaremetalPxePingServer (Shows the PXE PING servers currently defined for bare metal
        hosts)</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>addNicToVirtualMachine (Adds a new NIC to the specified VM on a selected network; see
          <xref linkend="multiple-ip-nic"/>)</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>removeNicFromVirtualMachine (Removes the specified NIC from a selected VM.)</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>updateDefaultNicForVirtualMachine (Updates the specified NIC to be the default one for a
        selected VM.)</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>addRegion (Registers a Region into another Region; see <xref linkend="regions"/>)</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>updateRegion (Updates Region details: ID, Name, Endpoint, User API Key, and User Secret
        Key.)</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>removeRegion (Removes a Region from current Region.)</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>listRegions (Get all the Regions. They can be filtered by using the ID or Name.)</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>getUser (This API can only be used by the Admin. Get user account details by using the
        API Key.) </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>getApiLimit (Show number of remaining APIs for the invoking user in current
        window)</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>resetApiLimit (For root admin, if account ID parameter is passed, it will reset count
        for that particular account, otherwise it will reset all counters)</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>lockAccount (Locks an account)</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>lockUser (Locks a user account)</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>scaleVirtualMachine (Scales the virtual machine to a new service offering.) </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>migrateVirtualMachineWithVolume (Attempts migrating VM with its volumes to a different
        host.) </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>dedicatePublicIpRange (Dedicates a Public IP range to an account.) </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>releasePublicIpRange (Releases a Public IP range back to the system pool.) </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>dedicateGuestVlanRange (Dedicates a guest VLAN range to an account.) </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>releaseDedicatedGuestVlanRange (Releases a dedicated guest VLAN range to the system.)
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>listDedicatedGuestVlanRanges (Lists dedicated guest VLAN ranges.) </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>updatePortForwardingRule (Updates a port forwarding rule. Only the private port and the
        VM can be updated.) </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>scaleSystemVm (Scale the service offering for a systemVM, console proxy, or secondary
        storage. The system VM must be in Stopped state for this command to take effect.) </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>listDeploymentPlanners (Lists all the deployment planners available.) </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>addS3 (Adds a Amazon Simple Storage Service instance.) </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>listS3s (Lists all the Amazon Simple Storage Service instances.) </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>findHostsForMigration (Find hosts suitable for migrating a VM to.) </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>releaseHostReservation (Releases host reservation.) </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>resizeVolume (Resizes a volume.) </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>updateVolume (Updates the volume.) </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>listStorageProviders (Lists storage providers.) </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>findStoragePoolsForMigration (Lists storage pools available for migrating a volume.)
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>createEgressFirewallRule (Creates a egress firewall rule for a given network. ) </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>deleteEgressFirewallRule (Deletes an egress firewall rule.) </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>listEgressFirewallRules (Lists all egress firewall rules for network.) </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>updateNetworkACLItem (Updates ACL item with specified ID.) </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>createNetworkACLList (Creates a Network ACL for the given VPC.) </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>deleteNetworkACLList (Deletes a Network ACL.) </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>replaceNetworkACLList (Replaces ACL associated with a Network or private gateway.)
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>listNetworkACLLists (Lists all network ACLs.) </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>addResourceDetail (Adds detail for the Resource.) </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>removeResourceDetail (Removes detail for the Resource.) </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>listResourceDetails (List resource details.) </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>addNiciraNvpDevice (Adds a Nicira NVP device.) </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>deleteNiciraNvpDevice (Deletes a Nicira NVP device.) </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>listNiciraNvpDevices (Lists Nicira NVP devices.) </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>listNiciraNvpDeviceNetworks (Lists network that are using a Nicira NVP device.) </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>addBigSwitchVnsDevice (Adds a BigSwitch VNS device.) </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>deleteBigSwitchVnsDevice (Deletes a BigSwitch VNS device.) </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>listBigSwitchVnsDevices (Lists BigSwitch VNS devices.) </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>configureSimulator (Configures a simulator.) </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>listApis (Lists all the available APIs on the server, provided by the API Discovery
        plugin.) </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>getApiLimit (Get the API limit count for the caller.) </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>resetApiLimit (Reset the API count.) </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>assignToGlobalLoadBalancerRule (Assign load balancer rule or list of load balancer rules
        to a global load balancer rules.) </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>removeFromGlobalLoadBalancerRule (Removes a load balancer rule association with global
        load balancer rule) </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>listVMSnapshot (List virtual machine snapshot by conditions) </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>createLoadBalancer (Creates a Load Balancer) </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>listLoadBalancers (Lists Load Balancers) </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>deleteLoadBalancer (Deletes a load balancer) </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>configureInternalLoadBalancerElement (Configures an Internal Load Balancer element.)
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>createInternalLoadBalancerElement (Create an Internal Load Balancer element.) </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>listInternalLoadBalancerElements (Lists all available Internal Load Balancer elements.)
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>createAffinityGroup (Creates an affinity or anti-affinity group.) </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>deleteAffinityGroup (Deletes an affinity group.) </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>listAffinityGroups (Lists all the affinity groups.)</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>updateVMAffinityGroup (Updates the affinity or anti-affinity group associations of a VM.
        The VM has to be stopped and restarted for the new properties to take effect.) </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>listAffinityGroupTypes (Lists affinity group types available.) </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>stopInternalLoadBalancerVM (Stops an Internal LB VM.) </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>startInternalLoadBalancerVM (Starts an existing Internal LB VM.) </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>listInternalLoadBalancerVMs (List internal LB VMs.) </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>listNetworkIsolationMethods (Lists supported methods of network isolation.) </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>dedicateZone (Dedicates a zone.) </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>dedicatePod (Dedicates a pod.) </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>dedicateCluster (Dedicate an existing cluster.) </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>dedicateHost (Dedicates a host.) </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>releaseDedicatedZone (Release dedication of zone.) </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>releaseDedicatedPod (Release dedication for the pod.) </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>releaseDedicatedCluster (Release dedication for cluster.) </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>releaseDedicatedHost (Release dedication for host.) </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>listDedicatedZones (List dedicated zones.) </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>listDedicatedPods (Lists dedicated pods.) </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>listDedicatedClusters (Lists dedicated clusters.) </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>listDedicatedHosts (Lists dedicated hosts.) </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
</section>
