<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "cloudstack.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>

<!-- Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
 or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
 distributed with this work for additional information
 regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
 to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
 "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
 with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
 
   http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
 
 Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
 software distributed under the License is distributed on an
 "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
 KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
 specific language governing permissions and limitations
 under the License.
-->

<section id="admin-alerts">
    <title>Administrator Alerts</title>
    <para>The system provides alerts and events to help with the management of the cloud. Alerts are notices to an administrator, generally delivered by e-mail, notifying the administrator that an error has occurred in the cloud. Alert behavior is configurable.</para>
    <para>Events track all of the user and administrator actions in the cloud. For example, every guest VM start creates an associated event. Events are stored in the Management Server’s database.</para>
    <para>Emails will be sent to administrators under the following circumstances:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>The Management Server cluster runs low on CPU, memory, or storage resources</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>The Management Server loses heartbeat from a Host for more than 3 minutes</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>The Host cluster runs low on CPU, memory, or storage resources</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <section id="external-snmp-manager">
        <!-- CLOUDSTACK-680 -->
        <title>Sending Alerts to External SNMP and Syslog Managers</title>
        <para>In addition to showing administrator alerts on the Dashboard in the &PRODUCT; UI and
            sending them in email, &PRODUCT; can also send the same alerts to external SNMP or
            Syslog management software. This is useful if you prefer to use an SNMP or Syslog
            manager to monitor your cloud.</para>
        <para>The alerts which can be sent are listed in <xref linkend="alerts"/>. You can also
            display the most up to date list by calling the API command listAlerts.</para>
        <section id="snmp-alert-details">
            <title>SNMP Alert Details</title>
            <para>The supported protocol is SNMP version 2.</para>
            <para>Each SNMP trap contains the following information: message, podId, dataCenterId, clusterId, and generationTime.</para>
        </section>
        <section id="syslog-alert-details">
            <title>Syslog Alert Details</title>
            <para>&PRODUCT; generates a syslog message for every alert. Each syslog message incudes
                the fields alertType, message, podId, dataCenterId, and clusterId, in the following
                format. If any field does not have a valid value, it will not be included.</para>
            <programlisting>Date severity_level Management_Server_IP_Address/Name  alertType:: value dataCenterId:: value  podId:: value  clusterId:: value  message:: value</programlisting>
            <para>For example:</para>
            <programlisting>Mar  4 10:13:47    WARN    localhost    alertType:: managementNode message:: Management server node 127.0.0.1 is up</programlisting>
        </section>
        <section id="snmp-syslog-config">
            <title>Configuring SNMP and Syslog Managers</title>
            <para>To configure one or more SNMP managers or Syslog managers to receive alerts from
                &PRODUCT;:</para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem><para>For an SNMP manager, install the &PRODUCT; MIB file on your SNMP manager system.
                    This maps the SNMP OIDs to trap types that can be more easily read by users.
                    The file must be publicly available.
                    For more information on how to install this file, consult the documentation provided with the SNMP manager.</para></listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Edit the file /etc/cloudstack/management/log4j-cloud.xml.</para>
                    <programlisting># vi /etc/cloudstack/management/log4j-cloud.xml</programlisting>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Add an entry using the syntax shown below. Follow the appropriate example
                        depending on whether you are adding an SNMP manager or a Syslog manager. To specify
                        multiple external managers, separate the IP addresses and other configuration values
                        with commas (,).</para>
                    <note>
                        <para>The recommended maximum number of SNMP or Syslog managers is 20 for
                            each.</para>
                    </note>
                    <para/>
                    <para>The following example shows how to configure two SNMP managers at IP addresses
                        10.1.1.1 and 10.1.1.2. Substitute your own IP addresses, ports, and communities. Do
                        not change the other values (name, threshold, class, and layout values).</para>
                    <programlisting>&lt;appender name="SNMP" class="org.apache.cloudstack.alert.snmp.SnmpTrapAppender"&gt;
  &lt;param name="Threshold" value="WARN"/&gt;  &lt;!-- Do not edit. The alert feature assumes WARN. --&gt;
  &lt;param name="SnmpManagerIpAddresses" value="10.1.1.1,10.1.1.2"/&gt;
  &lt;param name="SnmpManagerPorts" value="162,162"/&gt;
  &lt;param name="SnmpManagerCommunities" value="public,public"/&gt;
  &lt;layout class="org.apache.cloudstack.alert.snmp.SnmpEnhancedPatternLayout"&gt; &lt;!-- Do not edit -->
    &lt;param name="PairDelimeter" value="//"/&gt;
    &lt;param name="KeyValueDelimeter" value="::"/&gt;
  &lt;/layout&gt;
&lt;/appender&gt;</programlisting>
                    <para>The following example shows how to configure two Syslog managers at IP
                        addresses 10.1.1.1 and 10.1.1.2. Substitute your own IP addresses. You can
                        set Facility to any syslog-defined value, such as LOCAL0 - LOCAL7. Do not
                        change the other values.</para>
                    <programlisting>&lt;appender name="ALERTSYSLOG"&gt;
  &lt;param name="Threshold" value="WARN"/&gt;
  &lt;param name="SyslogHosts" value="10.1.1.1,10.1.1.2"/&gt;
  &lt;param name="Facility" value="LOCAL6"/&gt;   
  &lt;layout&gt;
    &lt;param name="ConversionPattern" value=""/&gt;
  &lt;/layout&gt;
&lt;/appender&gt;</programlisting>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>If your cloud has multiple Management Server nodes, repeat these steps to edit
                        log4j-cloud.xml on every instance.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>If you have made these changes while the Management Server is running, wait a
                        few minutes for the change to take effect.</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Troubleshooting:</emphasis> If no alerts appear at the
                configured SNMP or Syslog manager after a reasonable amount of time, it is likely that
                there is an error in the syntax of the &lt;appender&gt; entry in log4j-cloud.xml. Check
                to be sure that the format and settings are correct.</para>
        </section>
        <section id="delete-snmp-syslog-manager">
            <title>Deleting an SNMP or Syslog Manager</title>
            <para>To remove an external SNMP manager or Syslog manager so that it no longer receives
                alerts from &PRODUCT;, remove the corresponding entry from the file
                /etc/cloudstack/management/log4j-cloud.xml.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
</section>
