<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "cloudstack.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>

<!-- Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
 or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
 distributed with this work for additional information
 regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
 to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
 "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
 with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
 
   http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
 
 Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
 software distributed under the License is distributed on an
 "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
 KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
 specific language governing permissions and limitations
 under the License.
-->

<section id="admin-alerts">
    <title>Administrator Alerts</title>
    <para>The system provides alerts and events to help with the management of the cloud. Alerts are notices to an administrator, generally delivered by e-mail, notifying the administrator that an error has occurred in the cloud. Alert behavior is configurable.</para>
    <para>Events track all of the user and administrator actions in the cloud. For example, every guest VM start creates an associated event. Events are stored in the Management Server’s database.</para>
    <para>Emails will be sent to administrators under the following circumstances:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>The Management Server cluster runs low on CPU, memory, or storage resources</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>The Management Server loses heartbeat from a Host for more than 3 minutes</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>The Host cluster runs low on CPU, memory, or storage resources</para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
  <section id="xs-hotfix-notification">
    <title>XenServer Hotfix Notification</title>
    <para>The Alerts area of the Dashboard in the &PRODUCT; UI shows notifications about new
      Citrix XenServer software updates as they become available. In this way, administrators
      can more easily be aware and take action when a hotfix is required to keep the XenServer
      hypervisor hosts up to date. &PRODUCT; gives notification only for hotfixes that are
      applicable to the XenServer software version currently running on hosts within the
      cloud. Before generating the alert, &PRODUCT; checks to be sure the hotfix has not
      already been installed.</para>
    <para>In addition to the alert in the Dashboard, all hotfixes available for XenServer hosts
      in the cloud are displayed under Events, when you open the Select View dropdown and
      choose Host Updates. You can also see the hotfixes available for a given host when
      you're viewing the host details (Infrastructure > Hosts > click host name), where you
      will see the Updates tab. </para>
    <para>You can get the same information about new XenServer hotfixes by calling these API
      commands:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">listHostUpdates</emphasis>&mdash;Tells which patches have and
          have not been applied to a given host</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">listHostsWithPendingUpdates</emphasis>&mdash;Tells which hosts
          have not received a given patch</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>&PRODUCT; checks for new hotfixes once a week. It can be configured to check for
      hotfixes more or less often through the global setting update.check.interval.</para>
    <para>&PRODUCT; knows where to find the web-based Citrix feed for XenServer hotfix updates.
      In the unlikely event that Citrix changes this URL, it can be configured through the
      global setting xen.update.url. You can also turn off the hotfix notification feature
      entirely using host.updates.enable.</para>
  </section>    
</section>
