<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "cloudstack.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>

<!-- Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
 or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
 distributed with this work for additional information
 regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
 to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
 "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
 with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
 
   http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
 
 Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
 software distributed under the License is distributed on an
 "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
 KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
 specific language governing permissions and limitations
 under the License.
-->

<section id="api-throttling">
  <title>Limiting the Rate of API Requests</title>
  <para>You can limit the rate at which API requests can be placed for each
    account. This is useful to avoid malicious attacks on the Management Server, prevent
    performance degradation, and provide fairness to all accounts.</para>
  <para>If the number of API calls exceeds the threshold, an error message is returned for any additional API calls.
    The caller will have to retry these API calls at another time.</para>
  <section id="api-throttling-configure">
    <title>Configuring the API Request Rate</title>
    <para>To control the API request rate, use the following global configuration
      settings:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>api.throttling.enabled - Enable/Disable API throttling. By default, this setting is false, so
        API throttling is not enabled.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>api.throttling.interval (in seconds) - Time interval during which the number of API requests is to be counted.
        When the interval has passed, the API count is reset to 0.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>api.throttling.max - Maximum number of APIs that can be placed within the api.throttling.interval period.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>api.throttling.cachesize - Cache size for storing API counters.
        Use a value higher than the total number of accounts managed by the cloud.
        One cache entry is needed for each account, to store the running API total for that account.
      </para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section id="api-throttling-limitations">
    <title>Limitations on API Throttling</title>
    <para>The following limitations exist in the current implementation of this feature.</para>
    <note><para>Even with these limitations, &PRODUCT; is still able to effectively use API throttling to
      avoid malicious attacks causing denial of service.</para></note>
    <para/>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>In a deployment with multiple Management Servers,
        the cache is not synchronized across them.
        In this case, &PRODUCT; might not be able to
        ensure that only the exact desired number of API requests are allowed.
        In the worst case, the number of API calls that might be allowed is
        (number of Management Servers) * (api.throttling.max).
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>The API commands resetApiLimit and getApiLimit are limited to the
        Management Server where the API is invoked.
      </para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>        
  </section>
</section>