<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "cloudstack.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>

<!-- Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
 or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
 distributed with this work for additional information
 regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
 to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
 "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
 with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
 
   http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
 
 Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
 software distributed under the License is distributed on an
 "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
 KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
 specific language governing permissions and limitations
 under the License.
-->

<section id="aws-ec2-introduction">
  <title>Amazon Web Services EC2 Compatible Interface</title>
    <para>&PRODUCT; can translate Amazon Web Services (AWS) API calls to native &PRODUCT; API calls so that users can continue using existing AWS-compatible tools. This translation service runs as a separate web application in the same tomcat server as the management server of &PRODUCT;, listening on the same port. This Amazon EC2-compatible API is accessible through a SOAP web service as well as the REST query interface.</para>
    <warning>
	  <para>Expect the SOAP service to be deprecated in new releases in favor of the REST interface.</para>
    </warning> 
    <note>
      <para>This service was previously enabled by a separate software called CloudBridge, it is now fully integrated with the &PRODUCT; management server.
      </para>
    </note>
    <para>Limitations</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Supported only in zones that use basic networking.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Available in fresh installations of &PRODUCT;. Not available through upgrade of previous versions.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>If you need to support features such as elastic IP, set up a Citrix NetScaler to provide this service. The commands such as ec2-associate-address will not work without EIP setup. Users running VMs in this zone will be using the NetScaler-enabled network offering (DefaultSharedNetscalerEIP and ELBNetworkOffering).</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
</section>
