<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "cloudstack.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>

<!-- Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
    or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
    distributed with this work for additional information
    regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
    to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
    "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
    with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
    
    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
    
    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
    software distributed under the License is distributed on an
    "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
    KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
    specific language governing permissions and limitations
    under the License.
-->
<section id="basic-zone-network-traffic-types">
	<title>Basic Zone Network Traffic Types</title>
    <para>When basic networking is used, there can be only one physical network in the zone. That physical network carries the following traffic types:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>Guest. When end users run VMs, they generate guest traffic. The guest VMs communicate with each other over a network that can be referred to as the guest network. Each pod in a basic zone is a broadcast domain, and therefore each pod has a different IP range for the guest network. The administrator must configure the IP range for each pod.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Management. When &PRODUCT;'s internal resources communicate with each other, they generate management traffic. This includes communication between hosts, system VMs (VMs used by &PRODUCT; to perform various tasks in the cloud), and any other component that communicates directly with the &PRODUCT; Management Server. You must configure the IP range for the system VMs to use.</para>
            <note><para>We strongly recommend the use of separate NICs for management traffic and guest traffic.</para></note></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Public. Public traffic is generated when VMs in the cloud access the Internet. Publicly accessible IPs must be allocated for this purpose. End users can use the &PRODUCT; UI to acquire these IPs to implement NAT between their guest network and the public network, as described in Acquiring a New IP Address.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Storage. While labeled "storage" this is specifically about secondary storage, and doesn't affect traffic for primary storage. This includes traffic such as VM templates and snapshots, which is sent between the secondary storage VM and secondary storage servers. &PRODUCT; uses a separate Network Interface Controller (NIC) named storage NIC for storage network traffic. Use of a storage NIC that always operates on a high bandwidth network allows fast template and snapshot copying. You must configure the IP range to use for the storage network.</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>In a basic network, configuring the physical network is fairly straightforward. In most cases, you only need to configure one guest network to carry traffic that is generated by guest VMs. If you use a NetScaler load balancer and enable its elastic IP and elastic load balancing (EIP and ELB) features, you must also configure a network to carry public traffic. &PRODUCT; takes care of presenting the necessary network configuration steps to you in the UI when you add a new zone.</para>
</section>
