<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "cloudstack.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<!-- Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
        or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
        distributed with this work for additional information
        regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
        to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
        "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
        with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
        
        http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
        
        Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
        software distributed under the License is distributed on an
        "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
        KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
        specific language governing permissions and limitations
        under the License.
-->

<section id="best-practices-vm">
    <title>Best Practices for Virtual Machines</title>
    <para>For VMs to work as expected and provide excellent service, follow these guidelines.</para>
    <section id="best-practices-vm-monitoring">
    <title>Monitor VMs for Max Capacity</title>
	<para>The &PRODUCT; administrator should monitor the total number of VM instances in each
        cluster, and disable allocation to the cluster if the total is approaching the maximum that
        the hypervisor can handle. Be sure to leave a safety margin to allow for the possibility of
        one or more hosts failing, which would increase the VM load on the other hosts as the VMs
        are automatically redeployed. Consult the documentation for your chosen hypervisor to find
        the maximum permitted number of VMs per host, then use &PRODUCT; global configuration
        settings to set this as the default limit. Monitor the VM activity in each cluster at all
        times. Keep the total number of VMs below a safe level that allows for the occasional host
        failure. For example, if there are N hosts in the cluster, and you want to allow for one
        host in the cluster to be down at any given time, the total number of VM instances you can
        permit in the cluster is at most (N-1) * (per-host-limit). Once a cluster reaches this
        number of VMs, use the &PRODUCT; UI to disable allocation of more VMs to the
        cluster.</para>
    </section>
    <section id="best-practices-vm-tools">
    <title>Install Required Tools and Drivers</title>
        <para>Be sure the following are installed on each VM:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
                <listitem><para>For XenServer, install PV drivers and Xen tools on each VM.
                    This will enable live migration and clean guest shutdown.
                    Xen tools are required in order for dynamic CPU and RAM scaling to work.</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>For vSphere, install VMware Tools on each VM.
                    This will enable console view to work properly.
                    VMware Tools are required in order for dynamic CPU and RAM scaling to work.</para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>To be sure that Xen tools or VMware Tools is installed, use one of the following techniques:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem><para>Create each VM from a template that already has the tools installed; or,</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>When registering a new template, the administrator or user can indicate whether tools are
                                        installed on the template. This can be done through the UI
                                        or using the updateTemplate API; or,</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>If a user deploys a virtual machine with a template that does not have
                Xen tools or VMware Tools, and later installs the tools on the VM,
                then the user can inform &PRODUCT; using the updateVirtualMachine API.
                After installing the tools and updating the virtual machine, stop
                and start the VM.</para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>           
    </section>
</section>
