<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "cloudstack.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>

<!-- Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
 or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
 distributed with this work for additional information
 regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
 to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
 "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
 with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
 
   http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
 
 Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
 software distributed under the License is distributed on an
 "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
 KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
 specific language governing permissions and limitations
 under the License.
-->
<section id="citrix-xenserver-installation">
  <title>Citrix XenServer Installation for &PRODUCT;</title>
  <para>If you want to use the Citrix XenServer hypervisor to run guest virtual machines, install
    XenServer 6.0 or XenServer 6.0.2 on the host(s) in your cloud. For an initial installation,
    follow the steps below. If you have previously installed XenServer and want to upgrade to
    another version, see <xref linkend="xenserver-version-upgrading"/>.</para>
  <section id="system-requirements-xenserver-hosts">
    <title>System Requirements for XenServer Hosts</title>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The host must be certified as compatible with one of the following. See the Citrix
          Hardware Compatibility Guide: <ulink url="http://hcl.xensource.com"
            >http://hcl.xensource.com</ulink></para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>XenServer 5.6 SP2</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>XenServer 6.0</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>XenServer 6.0.2</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>You must re-install Citrix XenServer if you are going to re-use a host from a previous
          install.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Must support HVM (Intel-VT or AMD-V enabled)</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Be sure all the hotfixes provided by the hypervisor vendor are applied. Track the
          release of hypervisor patches through your hypervisor vendor’s support channel, and apply
          patches as soon as possible after they are released. &PRODUCT; will not track or notify
          you of required hypervisor patches. It is essential that your hosts are completely up to
          date with the provided hypervisor patches. The hypervisor vendor is likely to refuse to
          support any system that is not up to date with patches.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>All hosts within a cluster must be homogeneous. The CPUs must be of the same type,
          count, and feature flags.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Must support HVM (Intel-VT or AMD-V enabled in BIOS)</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>64-bit x86 CPU (more cores results in better performance)</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Hardware virtualization support required</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>4 GB of memory</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>36 GB of local disk</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>At least 1 NIC</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Statically allocated IP Address</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>When you deploy &PRODUCT;, the hypervisor host must not have any VMs already
          running</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <warning>
      <para>The lack of up-do-date hotfixes can lead to data corruption and lost VMs.</para>
    </warning>
  </section>
  <section id="xenserver-installation-steps">
    <title>XenServer Installation Steps</title>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>From <ulink url="https://www.citrix.com/English/ss/downloads/"
            >https://www.citrix.com/English/ss/downloads/</ulink>, download the appropriate version
          of XenServer for your &PRODUCT; version (see <xref
            linkend="system-requirements-xenserver-hosts"/>). Install it using the Citrix XenServer
          Installation Guide.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>After installation, perform the following configuration steps, which are described in
          the next few sections:</para>
        <informaltable frame="all">
          <tgroup cols="2" align="left" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
            <colspec colname="c1"/>
            <colspec colname="c2"/>
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry><para>Required</para></entry>
                <entry><para>Optional</para></entry>
              </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry><para><xref linkend="config-xenserver-dom0-memory"/></para></entry>
                <entry><para><xref linkend="xenserver-support-pkg-installation"/></para></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><para><xref linkend="xenserver-username-password"/></para></entry>
                <entry><para>Set up SR if not using NFS, iSCSI, or local disk; see <xref
                      linkend="xenserver-primary-storage-setup"/></para></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><para><xref linkend="xenserver-time-sync"/></para></entry>
                <entry><para><xref linkend="xenserver-iscsi-multipath-setup"/></para></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><para><xref linkend="xenserver-get-deploy-license"/></para></entry>
                <entry><para><xref linkend="xenserver-physical-network-setup"/></para></entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </informaltable>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
  <section id="config-xenserver-dom0-memory">
    <title>Configure XenServer dom0 Memory</title>
    <para>Configure the XenServer dom0 settings to allocate more memory to dom0. This can enable
      XenServer to handle larger numbers of virtual machines. We recommend 2940 MB of RAM for
      XenServer dom0. For instructions on how to do this, see <ulink
        url="http://support.citrix.com/article/CTX126531"
        >http://support.citrix.com/article/CTX126531</ulink>. The article refers to XenServer 5.6,
      but the same information applies to XenServer 6.0.</para>
  </section>
  <section id="xenserver-username-password">
    <title>Username and Password</title>
    <para>All XenServers in a cluster must have the same username and password as configured in
      &PRODUCT;.</para>
  </section>
  <section id="xenserver-time-sync">
    <title>Time Synchronization</title>
    <para>The host must be set to use NTP. All hosts in a pod must have the same time.</para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Install NTP.</para>
        <programlisting># yum install ntp</programlisting>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Edit the NTP configuration file to point to your NTP server.</para>
        <programlisting># vi /etc/ntp.conf</programlisting>
        <para>Add one or more server lines in this file with the names of the NTP servers you want
          to use. For example:</para>
        <programlisting>server 0.xenserver.pool.ntp.org
server 1.xenserver.pool.ntp.org
server 2.xenserver.pool.ntp.org
server 3.xenserver.pool.ntp.org
    </programlisting>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Restart the NTP client.</para>
        <programlisting># service ntpd restart</programlisting>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Make sure NTP will start again upon reboot.</para>
        <programlisting># chkconfig ntpd on</programlisting>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
  <section id="xenserver-licensing">
    <title>Licensing</title>
    <para>Citrix XenServer Free version provides 30 days usage without a license. Following the 30
      day trial, XenServer requires a free activation and license. You can choose to install a
      license now or skip this step. If you skip this step, you will need to install a license when
      you activate and license the XenServer.</para>
    <section id="xenserver-get-deploy-license">
      <title>Getting and Deploying a License</title>
      <para>If you choose to install a license now you will need to use the XenCenter to activate
        and get a license.</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>In XenCenter, click Tools > License manager.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Select your XenServer and select Activate Free XenServer.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Request a license.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <para>You can install the license with XenCenter or using the xe command line tool.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section id="xenserver-support-pkg-installation">
    <title>Install &PRODUCT; XenServer Support Package (CSP)</title>
    <para>(Optional)</para>
    <para>To enable security groups, elastic load balancing, and elastic IP on XenServer, download
      and install the &PRODUCT; XenServer Support Package (CSP). After installing XenServer, perform
      the following additional steps on each XenServer host.</para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Download the CSP software onto the XenServer host from one of the following
          links:</para>
        <para>For XenServer 6.0.2:</para>
        <para><ulink
            url="http://download.cloud.com/releases/3.0.1/XS-6.0.2/xenserver-cloud-supp.tgz"
            >http://download.cloud.com/releases/3.0.1/XS-6.0.2/xenserver-cloud-supp.tgz</ulink></para>
        <para>For XenServer 5.6 SP2:</para>
        <para><ulink url="http://download.cloud.com/releases/2.2.0/xenserver-cloud-supp.tgz"
            >http://download.cloud.com/releases/2.2.0/xenserver-cloud-supp.tgz</ulink></para>
        <para>For XenServer 6.0:</para>
        <para><ulink url="http://download.cloud.com/releases/3.0/xenserver-cloud-supp.tgz"
            >http://download.cloud.com/releases/3.0/xenserver-cloud-supp.tgz</ulink></para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Extract the file:</para>
        <programlisting># tar xf xenserver-cloud-supp.tgz</programlisting>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Run the following script:</para>
        <programlisting># xe-install-supplemental-pack xenserver-cloud-supp.iso</programlisting>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>If the XenServer host is part of a zone that uses basic networking, disable Open
          vSwitch (OVS):</para>
        <programlisting># xe-switch-network-backend  bridge</programlisting>
        <para>Restart the host machine when prompted.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <para>The XenServer host is now ready to be added to &PRODUCT;.</para>
  </section>
  <section id="xenserver-primary-storage-setup">
    <title>Primary Storage Setup for XenServer</title>
    <para>&PRODUCT; natively supports NFS, iSCSI and local storage. If you are using one of these
      storage types, there is no need to create the XenServer Storage Repository ("SR").</para>
    <para>If, however, you would like to use storage connected via some other technology, such as
      FiberChannel, you must set up the SR yourself. To do so, perform the following steps. If you
      have your hosts in a XenServer pool, perform the steps on the master node. If you are working
      with a single XenServer which is not part of a cluster, perform the steps on that
      XenServer.</para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Connect FiberChannel cable to all hosts in the cluster and to the FiberChannel storage
          host.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem id="rescan-scsi">
        <para>Rescan the SCSI bus. Either use the following command or use XenCenter to perform an
          HBA rescan.</para>
        <programlisting># scsi-rescan</programlisting>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
          <para>Repeat step <xref linkend="rescan-scsi"/> on every host.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem id="verify-scsi">
        <para>Check to be sure you see the new SCSI disk.</para>
        <programlisting># ls /dev/disk/by-id/scsi-360a98000503365344e6f6177615a516b -l</programlisting>
        <para>The output should look like this, although the specific file name will be different
          (scsi-&lt;scsiID&gt;):</para>
        <programlisting>lrwxrwxrwx 1 root root 9 Mar 16 13:47
/dev/disk/by-id/scsi-360a98000503365344e6f6177615a516b -> ../../sdc
    </programlisting>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
          <para>Repeat step <xref linkend="verify-scsi"/> on every host.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>On the storage server, run this command to get a unique ID for the new SR.</para>
        <programlisting># uuidgen</programlisting>
        <para>The output should look like this, although the specific ID will be different:</para>
        <programlisting>e6849e96-86c3-4f2c-8fcc-350cc711be3d</programlisting>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Create the FiberChannel SR. In name-label, use the unique ID you just
          generated.</para>
        <programlisting>
# xe sr-create type=lvmohba shared=true
device-config:SCSIid=360a98000503365344e6f6177615a516b
name-label=&quot;e6849e96-86c3-4f2c-8fcc-350cc711be3d&quot;
    </programlisting>
        <para>This command returns a unique ID for the SR, like the following example (your ID will
          be different):</para>
        <programlisting>7a143820-e893-6c6a-236e-472da6ee66bf</programlisting>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>To create a human-readable description for the SR, use the following command. In uuid,
          use the SR ID returned by the previous command. In name-description, set whatever friendly
          text you prefer.</para>
        <programlisting># xe sr-param-set uuid=7a143820-e893-6c6a-236e-472da6ee66bf name-description=&quot;Fiber Channel storage repository&quot;</programlisting>
        <para>Make note of the values you will need when you add this storage to &PRODUCT; later
          (see <xref linkend="primary-storage-add"/>). In the Add Primary Storage dialog, in
          Protocol, you will choose PreSetup. In SR Name-Label, you will enter the name-label you
          set earlier (in this example, e6849e96-86c3-4f2c-8fcc-350cc711be3d).</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>(Optional) If you want to enable multipath I/O on a FiberChannel SAN, refer to the
          documentation provided by the SAN vendor.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
  <section id="xenserver-iscsi-multipath-setup">
    <title>iSCSI Multipath Setup for XenServer (Optional)</title>
    <para>When setting up the storage repository on a Citrix XenServer, you can enable multipath
      I/O, which uses redundant physical components to provide greater reliability in the connection
      between the server and the SAN. To enable multipathing, use a SAN solution that is supported
      for Citrix servers and follow the procedures in Citrix documentation. The following links
      provide a starting point:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><ulink url="http://support.citrix.com/article/CTX118791"
            >http://support.citrix.com/article/CTX118791</ulink></para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><ulink url="http://support.citrix.com/article/CTX125403"
            >http://support.citrix.com/article/CTX125403</ulink></para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>You can also ask your SAN vendor for advice about setting up your Citrix repository for
      multipathing.</para>
    <para>Make note of the values you will need when you add this storage to the &PRODUCT; later
      (see <xref linkend="primary-storage-add"/>). In the Add Primary Storage dialog, in Protocol,
      you will choose PreSetup. In SR Name-Label, you will enter the same name used to create the
      SR.</para>
    <para>If you encounter difficulty, address the support team for the SAN provided by your vendor.
      If they are not able to solve your issue, see Contacting Support.</para>
  </section>
  <section id="xenserver-physical-network-setup">
    <title>Physical Networking Setup for XenServer</title>
    <para>Once XenServer has been installed, you may need to do some additional network
      configuration. At this point in the installation, you should have a plan for what NICs the
      host will have and what traffic each NIC will carry. The NICs should be cabled as necessary to
      implement your plan.</para>
    <para>If you plan on using NIC bonding, the NICs on all hosts in the cluster must be cabled
      exactly the same. For example, if eth0 is in the private bond on one host in a cluster, then
      eth0 must be in the private bond on all hosts in the cluster.</para>
    <para>The IP address assigned for the management network interface must be static. It can be set
      on the host itself or obtained via static DHCP.</para>
    <para>&PRODUCT; configures network traffic of various types to use different NICs or bonds on
      the XenServer host. You can control this process and provide input to the Management Server
      through the use of XenServer network name labels. The name labels are placed on physical
      interfaces or bonds and configured in &PRODUCT;. In some simple cases the name labels are not
      required.</para>
    <section id="xenserver-public-network-config">
      <title>Configuring Public Network with a Dedicated NIC for XenServer (Optional)</title>
      <para>&PRODUCT; supports the use of a second NIC (or bonded pair of NICs, described in <xref
          linkend="xenserver-nic-bonding"/>) for the public network. If bonding is not used, the
        public network can be on any NIC and can be on different NICs on the hosts in a cluster. For
        example, the public network can be on eth0 on node A and eth1 on node B. However, the
        XenServer name-label for the public network must be identical across all hosts. The
        following examples set the network label to &quot;cloud-public&quot;. After the management
        server is installed and running you must configure it with the name of the chosen network
        label (e.g. &quot;cloud-public&quot;); this is discussed in <xref
          linkend="management-server-install-flow"/>.</para>
      <para>If you are using two NICs bonded together to create a public network, see <xref
          linkend="xenserver-nic-bonding"/>.</para>
      <para>If you are using a single dedicated NIC to provide public network access, follow this
        procedure on each new host that is added to &PRODUCT; before adding the host.</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Run xe network-list and find the public network. This is usually attached to the NIC
            that is public. Once you find the network make note of its UUID. Call this
            &lt;UUID-Public&gt;.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Run the following command.</para>
          <programlisting># xe network-param-set name-label=cloud-public uuid=&lt;UUID-Public&gt;</programlisting>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>
    <section id="xenserver-multi-guest-network-config">
      <title>Configuring Multiple Guest Networks for XenServer (Optional)</title>
      <para>&PRODUCT; supports the use of multiple guest networks with the XenServer hypervisor.
        Each network is assigned a name-label in XenServer. For example, you might have two networks
        with the labels &quot;cloud-guest&quot; and &quot;cloud-guest2&quot;. After the management
        server is installed and running, you must add the networks and use these labels so that
        &PRODUCT; is aware of the networks.</para>
      <para>Follow this procedure on each new host before adding the host to &PRODUCT;:</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Run xe network-list and find one of the guest networks. Once you find the network
            make note of its UUID. Call this &lt;UUID-Guest&gt;.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Run the following command, substituting your own name-label and uuid values.</para>
          <programlisting># xe network-param-set name-label=&lt;cloud-guestN&gt; uuid=&lt;UUID-Guest&gt;</programlisting>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Repeat these steps for each additional guest network, using a different name-label
            and uuid each time.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>
    <section id="xenserver-separate-storage-network">
      <title>Separate Storage Network for XenServer (Optional)</title>
      <para>You can optionally set up a separate storage network. This should be done first on the
        host, before implementing the bonding steps below. This can be done using one or two
        available NICs. With two NICs bonding may be done as above. It is the administrator&apos;s
        responsibility to set up a separate storage network.</para>
      <para>Give the storage network a different name-label than what will be given for other
        networks.</para>
      <para>For the separate storage network to work correctly, it must be the only interface that
        can ping the primary storage device&apos;s IP address. For example, if eth0 is the
        management network NIC, ping -I eth0 &lt;primary storage device IP&gt; must fail. In all
        deployments, secondary storage devices must be pingable from the management network NIC or
        bond. If a secondary storage device has been placed on the storage network, it must also be
        pingable via the storage network NIC or bond on the hosts as well.</para>
      <para>You can set up two separate storage networks as well. For example, if you intend to
        implement iSCSI multipath, dedicate two non-bonded NICs to multipath. Each of the two
        networks needs a unique name-label.</para>
      <para>If no bonding is done, the administrator must set up and name-label the separate storage
        network on all hosts (masters and slaves).</para>
      <para>Here is an example to set up eth5 to access a storage network on 172.16.0.0/24.</para>
      <programlisting>
# xe pif-list host-name-label=&apos;hostname&apos; device=eth5
uuid(RO): ab0d3dd4-5744-8fae-9693-a022c7a3471d
device ( RO): eth5
#xe pif-reconfigure-ip DNS=172.16.3.3 gateway=172.16.0.1 IP=172.16.0.55 mode=static netmask=255.255.255.0 uuid=ab0d3dd4-5744-8fae-9693-a022c7a3471d</programlisting>
    </section>
    <section id="xenserver-nic-bonding">
      <title>NIC Bonding for XenServer (Optional)</title>
      <para>XenServer supports Source Level Balancing (SLB) NIC bonding. Two NICs can be bonded
        together to carry public, private, and guest traffic, or some combination of these. Separate
        storage networks are also possible. Here are some example supported configurations:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>2 NICs on private, 2 NICs on public, 2 NICs on storage</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>2 NICs on private, 1 NIC on public, storage uses management network</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>2 NICs on private, 2 NICs on public, storage uses management network</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>1 NIC for private, public, and storage</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>All NIC bonding is optional.</para>
      <para>XenServer expects all nodes in a cluster will have the same network cabling and same
        bonds implemented. In an installation the master will be the first host that was added to
        the cluster and the slave hosts will be all subsequent hosts added to the cluster. The bonds
        present on the master set the expectation for hosts added to the cluster later. The
        procedure to set up bonds on the master and slaves are different, and are described below.
        There are several important implications of this:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>You must set bonds on the first host added to a cluster. Then you must use xe
            commands as below to establish the same bonds in the second and subsequent hosts added
            to a cluster.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Slave hosts in a cluster must be cabled exactly the same as the master. For example,
            if eth0 is in the private bond on the master, it must be in the management network for
            added slave hosts.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <section id="management-network-bonding">
        <title>Management Network Bonding</title>
        <para>The administrator must bond the management network NICs prior to adding the host to
          &PRODUCT;.</para>
      </section>
      <section id="first-host-private-bond">
        <title>Creating a Private Bond on the First Host in the Cluster</title>
        <para>Use the following steps to create a bond in XenServer. These steps should be run on
          only the first host in a cluster. This example creates the cloud-private network with two
          physical NICs (eth0 and eth1) bonded into it.</para>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Find the physical NICs that you want to bond together.</para>
            <programlisting># xe pif-list host-name-label=&apos;hostname&apos; device=eth0
# xe pif-list host-name-label=&apos;hostname&apos; device=eth1</programlisting>
            <para>These command shows the eth0 and eth1 NICs and their UUIDs. Substitute the ethX
              devices of your choice. Call the UUID&apos;s returned by the above command slave1-UUID
              and slave2-UUID.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Create a new network for the bond. For example, a new network with name
              &quot;cloud-private&quot;.</para>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">This label is important. &PRODUCT; looks for a network by a
                name you configure. You must use the same name-label for all hosts in the cloud for
                the management network.</emphasis></para>
            <programlisting># xe network-create name-label=cloud-private
# xe bond-create network-uuid=[uuid of cloud-private created above]
pif-uuids=[slave1-uuid],[slave2-uuid]</programlisting>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>Now you have a bonded pair that can be recognized by &PRODUCT; as the management
          network.</para>
      </section>
      <section id="public-network-bonding">
        <title>Public Network Bonding</title>
        <para>Bonding can be implemented on a separate, public network. The administrator is
          responsible for creating a bond for the public network if that network will be bonded and
          will be separate from the management network.</para>
      </section>
      <section id="first-host-public-network-bond">
        <title>Creating a Public Bond on the First Host in the Cluster</title>
        <para>These steps should be run on only the first host in a cluster. This example creates
          the cloud-public network with two physical NICs (eth2 and eth3) bonded into it.</para>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Find the physical NICs that you want to bond together.</para>
            <programlisting>#xe pif-list host-name-label=&apos;hostname&apos; device=eth2
# xe pif-list host-name-label=&apos;hostname&apos; device=eth3</programlisting>
            <para>These command shows the eth2 and eth3 NICs and their UUIDs. Substitute the ethX
              devices of your choice. Call the UUID&apos;s returned by the above command slave1-UUID
              and slave2-UUID.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Create a new network for the bond. For example, a new network with name
              &quot;cloud-public&quot;.</para>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">This label is important. &PRODUCT; looks for a network by a
                name you configure. You must use the same name-label for all hosts in the cloud for
                the public network.</emphasis></para>
            <programlisting># xe network-create name-label=cloud-public
# xe bond-create network-uuid=[uuid of cloud-public created above]
pif-uuids=[slave1-uuid],[slave2-uuid]</programlisting>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>Now you have a bonded pair that can be recognized by &PRODUCT; as the public
          network.</para>
      </section>
      <section id="adding-more-hosts">
        <title>Adding More Hosts to the Cluster</title>
        <para>With the bonds (if any) established on the master, you should add additional, slave
          hosts. Run the following command for all additional hosts to be added to the cluster. This
          will cause the host to join the master in a single XenServer pool.</para>
        <programlisting># xe pool-join master-address=[master IP] master-username=root
master-password=[your password]</programlisting>
      </section>
      <section id="complete-bonding-setup">
        <title>Complete the Bonding Setup Across the Cluster</title>
        <para>With all hosts added to the pool, run the cloud-setup-bond script. This script will
          complete the configuration and set up of the bonds across all hosts in the cluster.</para>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Copy the script from the Management Server in
              /usr/lib64/cloud/common/scripts/vm/hypervisor/xenserver/cloud-setup-bonding.sh to the
              master host and ensure it is executable.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Run the script:</para>
            <programlisting># ./cloud-setup-bonding.sh</programlisting>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>Now the bonds are set up and configured properly across the cluster.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section id="xenserver-version-upgrading">
    <title>Upgrading XenServer Versions</title>
    <para>This section tells how to upgrade XenServer software on &PRODUCT; hosts. The actual
      upgrade is described in XenServer documentation, but there are some additional steps you must
      perform before and after the upgrade.</para>
    <note>
      <para>Be sure the hardware is certified compatible with the new version of XenServer.</para>
    </note>
    <para>To upgrade XenServer:</para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Upgrade the database. On the Management Server node:</para>
        <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
          <listitem>
            <para>Back up the database:</para>
            <programlisting># mysqldump --user=root --databases cloud > cloud.backup.sql
# mysqldump --user=root --databases cloud_usage > cloud_usage.backup.sql</programlisting>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>You might need to change the OS type settings for VMs running on the upgraded
              hosts.</para>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>If you upgraded from XenServer 5.6 GA to XenServer 5.6 SP2, change any VMs
                  that have the OS type CentOS 5.5 (32-bit), Oracle Enterprise Linux 5.5 (32-bit),
                  or Red Hat Enterprise Linux 5.5 (32-bit) to Other Linux (32-bit). Change any VMs
                  that have the 64-bit versions of these same OS types to Other Linux
                  (64-bit).</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>If you upgraded from XenServer 5.6 SP2 to XenServer 6.0.2, change any VMs that
                  have the OS type CentOS 5.6 (32-bit), CentOS 5.7 (32-bit), Oracle Enterprise Linux
                  5.6 (32-bit), Oracle Enterprise Linux 5.7 (32-bit), Red Hat Enterprise Linux 5.6
                  (32-bit) , or Red Hat Enterprise Linux 5.7 (32-bit) to Other Linux (32-bit).
                  Change any VMs that have the 64-bit versions of these same OS types to Other Linux
                  (64-bit).</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>If you upgraded from XenServer 5.6 to XenServer 6.0.2, do all of the
                  above.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Restart the Management Server and Usage Server. You only need to do this once for
              all clusters.</para>
            <programlisting># service cloud-management start
# service cloud-usage start</programlisting>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Disconnect the XenServer cluster from &PRODUCT;.</para>
        <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
          <listitem>
            <para>Log in to the &PRODUCT; UI as root.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Navigate to the XenServer cluster, and click Actions – Unmanage.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Watch the cluster status until it shows Unmanaged.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Log in to one of the hosts in the cluster, and run this command to clean up the
          VLAN:</para>
        <programlisting># . /opt/xensource/bin/cloud-clean-vlan.sh</programlisting>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Still logged in to the host, run the upgrade preparation script:</para>
        <programlisting># /opt/xensource/bin/cloud-prepare-upgrade.sh</programlisting>
        <para>Troubleshooting: If you see the error &quot;can&apos;t eject CD,&quot; log in to the
          VM and umount the CD, then run the script again.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Upgrade the XenServer software on all hosts in the cluster. Upgrade the master
          first.</para>
        <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
          <listitem>
            <para>Live migrate all VMs on this host to other hosts. See the instructions for live
              migration in the Administrator&apos;s Guide.</para>
            <para>Troubleshooting: You might see the following error when you migrate a VM:</para>
            <programlisting>[root@xenserver-qa-2-49-4 ~]# xe vm-migrate live=true host=xenserver-qa-2-49-5 vm=i-2-8-VM
You attempted an operation on a VM which requires PV drivers to be installed but the drivers were not detected.
vm: b6cf79c8-02ee-050b-922f-49583d9f1a14 (i-2-8-VM)</programlisting>
            <para>To solve this issue, run the following:</para>
            <programlisting># /opt/xensource/bin/make_migratable.sh  b6cf79c8-02ee-050b-922f-49583d9f1a14</programlisting>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Reboot the host.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Upgrade to the newer version of XenServer. Use the steps in XenServer
              documentation.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>After the upgrade is complete, copy the following files from the management server
              to this host, in the directory locations shown below:</para>
            <informaltable frame="all">
              <tgroup cols="2" align="left" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
                <colspec colname="c1"/>
                <colspec colname="c2"/>
                <thead>
                  <row>
                    <entry><para>Copy this Management Server file...</para></entry>
                    <entry><para>...to this location on the XenServer host</para></entry>
                  </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <row>
                    <entry><para>/usr/lib64/cloud/common/scripts/vm/hypervisor/xenserver/xenserver60/NFSSR.py</para></entry>
                    <entry><para>/opt/xensource/sm/NFSSR.py</para></entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry><para>/usr/lib64/cloud/common/scripts/vm/hypervisor/xenserver/setupxenserver.sh</para></entry>
                    <entry><para>/opt/xensource/bin/setupxenserver.sh</para></entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry><para>/usr/lib64/cloud/common/scripts/vm/hypervisor/xenserver/make_migratable.sh</para></entry>
                    <entry><para>/opt/xensource/bin/make_migratable.sh</para></entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry><para>/usr/lib64/cloud/common/scripts/vm/hypervisor/xenserver/cloud-clean-vlan.sh</para></entry>
                    <entry><para>/opt/xensource/bin/cloud-clean-vlan.sh</para></entry>
                  </row>
                </tbody>
              </tgroup>
            </informaltable>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Run the following script:</para>
            <programlisting># /opt/xensource/bin/setupxenserver.sh</programlisting>
            <para>Troubleshooting: If you see the following error message, you can safely ignore
              it.</para>
            <programlisting>mv: cannot stat `/etc/cron.daily/logrotate&apos;: No such file or directory</programlisting>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Plug in the storage repositories (physical block devices) to the XenServer
              host:</para>
            <programlisting># for pbd in `xe pbd-list currently-attached=false| grep ^uuid | awk &apos;{print $NF}&apos;`; do xe pbd-plug uuid=$pbd ; done</programlisting>
            <para>Note: If you add a host to this XenServer pool, you need to migrate all VMs on
              this host to other hosts, and eject this host from XenServer pool.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Repeat these steps to upgrade every host in the cluster to the same version of
          XenServer.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Run the following command on one host in the XenServer cluster to clean up the host
          tags:</para>
        <programlisting># for host in $(xe host-list | grep ^uuid | awk &apos;{print $NF}&apos;) ; do xe host-param-clear uuid=$host param-name=tags; done;</programlisting>
        <note>
          <para>When copying and pasting a command, be sure the command has pasted as a single line
            before executing. Some document viewers may introduce unwanted line breaks in copied
            text.</para>
        </note>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Reconnect the XenServer cluster to &PRODUCT;.</para>
        <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
          <listitem>
            <para>Log in to the &PRODUCT; UI as root.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Navigate to the XenServer cluster, and click Actions – Manage.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Watch the status to see that all the hosts come up.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>After all hosts are up, run the following on one host in the cluster:</para>
        <programlisting># /opt/xensource/bin/cloud-clean-vlan.sh</programlisting>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
</section>
