<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "cloudstack.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>

<!-- Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
 or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
 distributed with this work for additional information
 regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
 to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
 "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
 with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
 
   http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
 
 Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
 software distributed under the License is distributed on an
 "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
 KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
 specific language governing permissions and limitations
 under the License.
-->

<section id="configure-guest-traffic-in-advanced-zone">
    <title>Configure Guest Traffic in an Advanced Zone</title>
    <para>These steps assume you have already logged in to the &PRODUCT; UI. To configure the base guest network:</para>
    <orderedlist>
        <listitem><para>In the left navigation, choose Infrastructure. On Zones, click View More, then click the zone to which you want to add a network.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Click the Network tab.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Click Add network.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Provide the following information:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem><para>Name. The name of the network.  This will be user-visible</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>Description: The description of the network.  This will be user-visible</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>VLAN ID: Enter an administrator-configured VLAN ID so you can create different networks for use by different VM users in the zone</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>Scope: Choose account-specific or domain-specific if you would like to make the network accessible to only a single account or domain.  Choose zone-wide if all accounts with access to the zone should be able to access the network.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>Domain/Account: If Scope is account-specific, enter the domain and account name for the account</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>Network offering: If the administrator has configured multiple network offerings, select the one you want to use for this network</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>Gateway: The gateway that the guests should use</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>Netmask: The netmask in use on the subnet the guests will use</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>Start IP/End IP: Enter the first and last IP addresses that define a range that &PRODUCT; can assign to guests. If one NIC is used, these IPs should be in the same CIDR as the pod CIDR.  If multiple NICs are used, they may be in a different subnet.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>Network Domain: (Optional) If you want to assign a special domain name to this network, specify the DNS suffix.</para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
        <listitem><para>Click OK.</para></listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    
    
    </section>
