<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "cloudstack.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>

<!-- Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
	or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
	distributed with this work for additional information
	regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
	to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
	"License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
	with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
	
	http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
	
	Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
	software distributed under the License is distributed on an
	"AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
	KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
	specific language governing permissions and limitations
	under the License.
-->
<section id="convert-hyperv-vm-to-template">
	<title>Converting a Hyper-V VM to a Template</title>
	<para>To convert a Hyper-V VM to a XenServer-compatible &PRODUCT; template, you will need a standalone XenServer host with an attached NFS VHD SR.  Use whatever XenServer version you are using with &PRODUCT;, but use XenCenter 5.6 FP1 or SP2 (it is backwards compatible to 5.6).  Additionally, it may help to have an attached NFS ISO SR.</para>
	<para>For Linux VMs, you may need to do some preparation in Hyper-V before trying to get the VM to work in XenServer.  Clone the VM and work on the clone if you still want to use the VM in Hyper-V.  Uninstall Hyper-V Integration Components and check for any references to device names in /etc/fstab:</para>
	<orderedlist>
		<listitem><para>From the linux_ic/drivers/dist directory, run make uninstall (where "linux_ic" is the path to the copied Hyper-V Integration Components files).</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>Restore the original initrd from backup in /boot/ (the backup is named *.backup0).</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>Remove the "hdX=noprobe" entries from /boot/grub/menu.lst.</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>Check /etc/fstab for any partitions mounted by device name. Change those entries (if any) to
				mount by LABEL or UUID. You can get that information with the blkid command.</para></listitem>
	</orderedlist>
	<para>The next step is make sure the VM is not running in Hyper-V, then get the VHD into XenServer.  There are two options for doing this.</para>
	<para>Option one:</para>
	<orderedlist>
	<listitem><para>Import the VHD using XenCenter.  In XenCenter, go to Tools&gt;Virtual Appliance Tools&gt;Disk Image Import.</para></listitem>		
		<listitem><para>Choose the VHD, then click Next.</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>Name the VM, choose the NFS VHD SR under Storage, enable "Run Operating System Fixups" and choose the NFS ISO SR.</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>Click Next, then Finish.  A VM should be created.</para></listitem>
	</orderedlist>
	<para>Option two:</para>
	<orderedlist>
		<listitem><para>Run XenConvert, under From choose VHD, under To choose XenServer. Click Next.</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>Choose the VHD, then click Next.</para></listitem>		
		<listitem><para>Input the XenServer host info, then click Next.</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>Name the VM, then click Next, then Convert. A VM should be created.</para></listitem>
	</orderedlist>
	<para>Once you have a VM created from the Hyper-V VHD, prepare it using the following steps:</para>
	<orderedlist>
		<listitem><para>Boot the VM, uninstall Hyper-V Integration Services, and reboot.</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>Install XenServer Tools, then reboot.</para></listitem>		
		<listitem><para>Prepare the VM as desired. For example, run sysprep on Windows VMs. See <xref linkend="create-windows-template"/>.</para></listitem>
	</orderedlist>
	<para>Either option above will create a VM in HVM mode.  This is fine for Windows VMs, but Linux VMs may not perform optimally.  Converting a Linux VM to PV mode will require additional steps and will vary by distribution.</para>
	<orderedlist>
		<listitem><para>Shut down the VM and copy the VHD from the NFS storage to a web server; for example, mount the NFS share on the web server and copy it, or from the XenServer host use sftp or scp to upload it to the web server.</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>In &PRODUCT;, create a new template using the following values:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para>URL. Give the URL for the VHD</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>OS Type. Use the appropriate OS. For PV mode on CentOS, choose Other PV (32-bit) or Other PV (64-bit). This choice is available only for XenServer.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Hypervisor. XenServer</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Format. VHD</para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist></listitem>
		
	</orderedlist>
	<para>The template will be created, and you can create instances from it.</para>
</section>
