<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "file:///C:/Program%20Files%20(x86)/Publican/DocBook_DTD/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "cloudstack.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<section id="creating-compute-offerings">
    <title>Creating a New Compute Offering</title>
    <para>To create a new compute offering:</para>
    <orderedlist>
        <listitem><para>Log in with admin privileges to the CloudPlatform UI.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>In the left navigation bar, click Service Offerings.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>In Select Offering, choose Compute Offering.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Click Add Compute Offering.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>In the dialog, make the following choices:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem><para>Name. Any desired name for the service offering.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>Description. A short description of the offering that can be displayed to users</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>Storage type. The type of disk that should be allocated. Local allocates from storage attached directly to the host where the system VM is running. Shared allocates from storage accessible via NFS.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para># of CPU cores. The number of cores which should be allocated to a system VM with this offering</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>CPU (in MHz). The CPU speed of the cores that the system VM is allocated. For example, “2000” would provide for a 2 GHz clock.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>Memory (in MB). The amount of memory in megabytes that the system VM should be allocated. For example, “2048” would provide for a 2 GB RAM allocation.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>Network Rate. Allowed data transfer rate in MB per second.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>Offer HA. If yes, the administrator can choose to have the system VM be monitored and as highly available as possible.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>Storage Tags.  The tags that should be associated with the primary storage used by the system VM.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>Host Tags.  (Optional) Any tags that you use to organize your hosts</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>CPU cap. Whether to limit the level of CPU usage even if spare capacity is available.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>Public.  Indicate whether the service offering should be available all domains or only some domains.  Choose Yes to make it available to all domains.  Choose No to limit the scope to a subdomain; CloudPlatform will then prompt for the subdomain's name.</para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist></listitem> 
        <listitem><para>Click Add.</para></listitem>        
    </orderedlist>                
    
    
</section>
