<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "cloudstack.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>

<!-- Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
    or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
    distributed with this work for additional information
    regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
    to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
    "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
    with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
    
    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
    
    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
    software distributed under the License is distributed on an
    "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
    KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
    specific language governing permissions and limitations
    under the License.
-->
<section id="creating-network-offerings">
  <title>Creating a New Network Offering</title>
  <para>To create a network offering:</para>
  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Log in with admin privileges to the &PRODUCT; UI.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>In the left navigation bar, click Service Offerings.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>In Select Offering, choose Network Offering.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Click Add Network Offering.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>In the dialog, make the following choices:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Name</emphasis>. Any desired name for the network
            offering.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis>. A short description of the offering
            that can be displayed to users.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Network Rate</emphasis>. Allowed data transfer rate in MB per
            second.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Guest Type</emphasis>. Choose whether the guest network is
            isolated or shared. </para>
          <para condition="admin">For a description of this term, see <xref
              linkend="about-virtual-networks"/>.</para>
          <para condition="install">For a description of this term, see the Administration Guide.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Persistent</emphasis>. Indicate whether the guest network is
            persistent or not. The network that you can provision without having to deploy a VM on
            it is termed persistent network. For more information, see <xref
              linkend="persistent-network"/>.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Specify VLAN</emphasis>. (Isolated guest networks only)
            Indicate whether a VLAN should be specified when this offering is used.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">VPC</emphasis>. This option indicate whether the guest network
            is Virtual Private Cloud-enabled. A Virtual Private Cloud (VPC) is a private, isolated
            part of &PRODUCT;. A VPC can have its own virtual network topology that resembles a
            traditional physical network. For more information on VPCs, see <xref linkend="vpc"/>.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Supported Services</emphasis>. Select one or more of the
            possible network services. For some services, you must also choose the service provider;
            for example, if you select Load Balancer, you can choose the &PRODUCT; virtual router or
            any other load balancers that have been configured in the cloud. Depending on which
            services you choose, additional fields may appear in the rest of the dialog box.</para>
          <para>Based on the guest network type selected, you can see the following supported
            services:</para>
          <informaltable>
            <tgroup cols="4" align="left" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
              <thead>
                <row>
                  <entry><para>Supported Services</para></entry>
                  <entry><para>Description</para></entry>
                  <entry><para>Isolated</para></entry>
                  <entry><para>Shared</para></entry>
                </row>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <row>
                  <entry><para>DHCP</para></entry>
                  <entry><para>For more information, see <xref linkend="dns-dhcp"/>.</para></entry>
                  <entry><para>Supported</para></entry>
                  <entry><para>Supported</para></entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry><para>DNS</para></entry>
                  <entry><para>For more information, see <xref linkend="dns-dhcp"/>.</para></entry>
                  <entry><para>Supported</para></entry>
                  <entry><para>Supported</para></entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry><para>Load Balancer</para></entry>
                  <entry><para>If you select Load Balancer, you can choose the &PRODUCT; virtual
                      router or any other load balancers that have been configured in the
                      cloud.</para></entry>
                  <entry><para>Supported</para></entry>
                  <entry><para>Supported</para></entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry><para>Firewall</para></entry>
                  <entry><para condition="install">For more information, see <xref
                        linkend="firewall-rules"/>.</para>
                    <para condition="admin">For more information, see the Administration
                      Guide.</para></entry>
                  <entry><para>Supported</para></entry>
                  <entry><para>Supported</para></entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry><para>Source NAT</para></entry>
                  <entry><para>If you select Source NAT, you can choose the &PRODUCT; virtual router
                      or any other Source NAT providers that have been configured in the
                      cloud.</para></entry>
                  <entry><para>Supported</para></entry>
                  <entry><para>Supported</para></entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry><para>Static NAT</para></entry>
                  <entry><para>If you select Static NAT, you can choose the &PRODUCT; virtual router
                      or any other Static NAT providers that have been configured in the
                      cloud.</para></entry>
                  <entry><para>Supported</para></entry>
                  <entry><para>Supported</para></entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry><para>Port Forwarding</para></entry>
                  <entry><para>If you select Port Forwarding, you can choose the &PRODUCT; virtual
                      router or any other Port Forwarding providers that have been configured in the
                      cloud.</para></entry>
                  <entry><para>Supported</para></entry>
                  <entry><para>Not Supported</para></entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry><para>VPN</para></entry>
                  <entry><para>For more information, see <xref linkend="vpn"/>.</para></entry>
                  <entry><para>Supported</para></entry>
                  <entry><para>Not Supported</para></entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry><para>User Data</para></entry>
                  <entry><para condition="admin">For more information, see <xref
                        linkend="user-data-and-meta-data"/>.</para>
                    <para condition="install">For more information, see the Administration
                      Guide.</para></entry>
                  <entry><para>Not Supported</para></entry>
                  <entry><para>Supported</para></entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry><para>Network ACL</para></entry>
                  <entry><para>For more information, see <xref linkend="configure-acl"
                    />.</para></entry>
                  <entry><para>Supported</para></entry>
                  <entry><para>Not Supported</para></entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry><para>Security Groups</para></entry>
                  <entry><para>For more information, see <xref linkend="add-security-group"
                      />.</para></entry>
                  <entry><para>Not Supported</para></entry>
                  <entry><para>Supported</para></entry>
                </row>
              </tbody>
            </tgroup>
          </informaltable>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">System Offering</emphasis>. If the service provider for any of
            the services selected in Supported Services is a virtual router, the System Offering
            field appears. Choose the system service offering that you want virtual routers to use
            in this network. For example, if you selected Load Balancer in Supported Services and
            selected a virtual router to provide load balancing, the System Offering field appears
            so you can choose between the &PRODUCT; default system service offering and any custom
            system service offerings that have been defined by the &PRODUCT; root
            administrator.</para>
          <para condition="admin">For more information, see <xref linkend="system-service-offerings"/>.</para>
          <para condition="install">For more information, see the Administration Guide.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">LB Isolation</emphasis>: Specify what type of load balancer
            isolation you want for the network: Shared or Dedicated.</para>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Dedicated</emphasis>: If you select dedicated LB isolation, a
            dedicated load balancer device is assigned for the network from the pool of dedicated
            load balancer devices provisioned in the zone. If no sufficient dedicated load balancer
            devices are available in the zone, network creation fails. Dedicated device is a good
            choice for the high-traffic networks that make full use of the device's
            resources.</para>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Shared</emphasis>: If you select shared LB isolation, a shared
            load balancer device is assigned for the network from the pool of shared load balancer
            devices provisioned in the zone. While provisioning &PRODUCT; picks the shared load
            balancer device that is used by the least number of accounts. Once the device reaches
            its maximum capacity, the device will not be allocated to a new account.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Mode</emphasis>: You can select either Inline mode or Side by
            Side mode:</para>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Inline mode</emphasis>: Supported only for Juniper SRX
            firewall and BigF5 load balancer devices. In inline mode, a firewall device is placed in
            front of a load balancing device. The firewall acts as the gateway for all the incoming
            traffic, then redirect the load balancing traffic to the load balancer behind it. The
            load balancer in this case will not have the direct access to the public network. </para>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Side by Side</emphasis>: In side by side mode, a firewall
            device is deployed in parallel with the load balancer device. So the traffic to the load
            balancer public IP is not routed through the firewall, and therefore, is exposed to the
            public network.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Associate Public IP</emphasis>: Select this option if you want
            to assign a public IP address to the VMs deployed in the guest network. This option is
            available only if</para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Guest network is shared.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>StaticNAT is enabled.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Elastic IP is enabled.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
          <para>For information on Elastic IP, see <xref linkend="elastic-ip"/>.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Redundant router capability</emphasis>. Available only when
            Virtual Router is selected as the Source NAT provider. Select this option if you want to
            use two virtual routers in the network for uninterrupted connection: one operating as
            the master virtual router and the other as the backup. The master virtual router
            receives requests from and sends responses to the user’s VM. The backup virtual router
            is activated only when the master is down. After the failover, the backup becomes the
            master virtual router. &PRODUCT; deploys the routers on different hosts to ensure
            reliability if one host is down.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Conserve mode</emphasis>. Indicate whether to use conserve
            mode. In this mode, network resources are allocated only when the first virtual machine
            starts in the network. When conservative mode is off, the public IP can only be used for
            a single service. For example, a public IP used for a port forwarding rule cannot be
            used for defining other services, such as SaticNAT or load balancing. When the conserve
            mode is on, you can define more than one service on the same public IP.</para>
          <note>
            <para>If StaticNAT is enabled, irrespective of the status of the conserve mode, no port
              forwarding or load balancing rule can be created for the IP. However, you can add the
              firewall rules by using the createFirewallRule command.</para>
          </note>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Tags</emphasis>. Network tag to specify which physical network
            to use.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Click Add.</para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
</section>
