<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "cloudstack.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>

<!-- Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
    or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
    distributed with this work for additional information
    regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
    to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
    "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
    with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
    software distributed under the License is distributed on an
    "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
    KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
    specific language governing permissions and limitations
    under the License.
-->
<section id="delete-event-alerts">
  <title>Deleting and Archiving Events and Alerts</title>
  <para>&PRODUCT; provides you the ability to delete or archive the existing alerts and events that
    you no longer want to implement. You can regularly delete or archive any alerts or events that
    you cannot, or do not want to resolve from the database.</para>
  <para>You can delete or archive individual alerts or events either directly by using the Quickview
    or by using the Details page. If you want to delete multiple alerts or events at the same time,
    you can use the respective context menu. You can delete alerts or events by category for a time
    period.</para>
  <para>In order to support the delete or archive alerts, the following global parameters have been
    added:</para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">alert.purge.delay</emphasis>: The alerts older than specified
        number of days are purged. Set the value to 0 to never purge alerts automatically.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">alert.purge.interval</emphasis>: The interval in seconds to wait
        before running the alert purge thread. The default is 86400 seconds (one day).</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <note>
    <para>Archived alerts or events cannot be viewed in the UI, or by using the API. They are
      maintained in the database for auditing or compliance purposes.</para>
  </note>
  <formalpara>
    <title>Permissions</title>
    <para>Consider the following:</para>
  </formalpara>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>The root admin can delete or archive one or multiple alerts or events.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>The domain admin or end user can delete or archive one or multiple events.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
</section>
