<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "cloudstack.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<!-- Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
  or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
  distributed with this work for additional information
  regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
  to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
  "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
  with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
  http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
  software distributed under the License is distributed on an
  "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
  KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
  specific language governing permissions and limitations
  under the License.
-->
<section id="egress-firewall-rule">
  <title>Creating Egress Firewall Rules in an Advanced Zone</title>
  <para>The egress traffic originates from a private network to a public network, such as the
    Internet. By default, the egress traffic is blocked, so no outgoing traffic is allowed from a
    guest network to the Internet. However, you can control the egress traffic in an Advanced zone
    by creating egress firewall rules. When an egress firewall rule is applied, the traffic specific
    to the rule is allowed and the remaining traffic is blocked. When all the firewall rules are
    removed the default policy, Block, is applied.</para>
  <para>Egress firewall rules are supported on Juniper SRX and virtual router.</para>
    <note>
    <para>The egress firewall rules are not supported on shared networks.</para>
  </note>
  <para>Consider the following scenarios to apply egress firewall rules:</para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Allow the egress traffic from specified source CIDR. The Source CIDR is part of guest
        network CIDR.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Allow the egress traffic with destination protocol TCP,UDP,ICMP, or ALL.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Allow the egress traffic with destination protocol and port range. The port range is
        specified for TCP, UDP or for ICMP type and code.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>To configure an egress firewall rule:</para>
  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Log in to the &PRODUCT; UI as an administrator or end user. </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>In the left navigation, choose Network.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>In Select view, choose Guest networks, then click the Guest network you want.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>To add an egress rule, click the Egress rules tab and fill out the following fields to
        specify what type of traffic is allowed to be sent out of VM instances in this guest
        network:</para>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="./images/egress-firewall-rule.png"/>
        </imageobject>
        <textobject>
          <phrase>egress-firewall-rule.png: adding an egress firewall rule</phrase>
        </textobject>
      </mediaobject>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">CIDR</emphasis>: (Add by CIDR only) To send traffic only to
            the IP addresses within a particular address block, enter a CIDR or a comma-separated
            list of CIDRs. The CIDR is the base IP address of the destination. For example,
            192.168.0.0/22. To allow all CIDRs, set to 0.0.0.0/0.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Protocol</emphasis>: The networking protocol that VMs uses to
            send outgoing traffic. The TCP and UDP protocols are typically used for data exchange
            and end-user communications. The ICMP protocol is typically used to send error messages
            or network monitoring data.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Start Port, End Port</emphasis>: (TCP, UDP only) A range of
            listening ports that are the destination for the outgoing traffic. If you are opening a
            single port, use the same number in both fields.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">ICMP Type, ICMP Code</emphasis>: (ICMP only) The type of
            message and error code that are sent.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Click Add.</para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
</section>
