<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "cloudstack.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<!-- Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
  or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
  distributed with this work for additional information
  regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
  to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
  "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
  with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
  http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
  software distributed under the License is distributed on an
  "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
  KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
  specific language governing permissions and limitations
  under the License.
-->
<section id="external-guest-lb-integration">
  <title>External Guest Load Balancer Integration (Optional)</title>
  <para>&PRODUCT; can optionally use a Citrix NetScaler or BigIP F5 load balancer to provide load
    balancing services to guests. If this is not enabled, &PRODUCT; will use the software load
    balancer in the virtual router.</para>
  <para>To install and enable an external load balancer for &PRODUCT; management:</para>
  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Set up the appliance according to the vendor's directions.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Connect it to the networks carrying public traffic and management traffic (these could
        be the same network).</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Record the IP address, username, password, public interface name, and private interface
        name. The interface names will be something like "1.1" or "1.2".</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Make sure that the VLANs are trunked to the management network interface.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>After the &PRODUCT; Management Server is installed, log in as administrator to the
        &PRODUCT; UI.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>In the left navigation bar, click Infrastructure.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>In Zones, click View More.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Choose the zone you want to work with.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Click the Network tab.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>In the Network Service Providers node of the diagram, click Configure. (You might have
        to scroll down to see this.)</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Click NetScaler or F5.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Click the Add button (+) and provide the following:</para>
      <para>For NetScaler:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>IP Address: The IP address of the SRX.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Username/Password: The authentication credentials to access the device. &PRODUCT;
            uses these credentials to access the device.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Type: The type of device that is being added. It could be F5 Big Ip Load Balancer,
            NetScaler VPX, NetScaler MPX, or NetScaler SDX. For a comparison of the NetScaler types,
            see the &PRODUCT; Administration Guide.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Public interface: Interface of device that is configured to be part of the public
            network.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Private interface: Interface of device that is configured to be part of the private
            network.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Number of retries. Number of times to attempt a command on the device before
            considering the operation failed. Default is 2.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Capacity: The number of networks the device can handle.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Dedicated: When marked as dedicated, this device will be dedicated to a single
            account. When Dedicated is checked, the value in the Capacity field has no significance
            implicitly, its value is 1.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Click OK.</para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
  <para>The installation and provisioning of the external load balancer is finished. You can proceed
    to add VMs and NAT or load balancing rules.</para>
</section>
