<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "cloudstack.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<!-- Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
  or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
  distributed with this work for additional information
  regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
  to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
  "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
  with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
  http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
  software distributed under the License is distributed on an
  "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
  KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
  specific language governing permissions and limitations
  under the License.
-->
<chapter id="global-config">
  <title>Global Configuration Parameters</title>
  <section id="setting-global-config-parameters">
  <title>Setting Global Configuration Parameters</title>
  <para>&PRODUCT; provides parameters that you can set to control many aspects of the cloud. When
    &PRODUCT; is first installed, and periodically thereafter, you might need to modify these
    settings.</para>
  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Log in to the UI as administrator.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>In the left navigation bar, click Global Settings.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>In Select View, choose one of the following:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Global Settings. This displays a list of the parameters with brief descriptions and
            current values.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Hypervisor Capabilities. This displays a list of hypervisor versions with the
            maximum number of guests supported for each.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Use the search box to narrow down the list to those you are interested in.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Click the Edit icon to modify a value. If you are viewing Hypervisor Capabilities, you
        must click the name of the hypervisor first to display the editing screen.</para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
  </section>
  <section id="about-global-config-parameters">
  <title>About Global Configuration Parameters</title>
    <para>&PRODUCT; provides a variety of settings you can use to set limits, configure features, 
      and enable or disable features in the cloud. Once your Management Server is running, you might 
      need to set some of these global configuration parameters, depending on what optional features 
      you are setting up.</para>
    <para>To modify global configuration parameters, use the steps in "Setting Global Configuration 
      Parameters."</para>
    <para>The documentation for each &PRODUCT; feature should direct you to the names of the applicable
      parameters. Many of them are discussed in the &PRODUCT; Administration Guide. The following table 
      shows a few of the more useful parameters.</para>
    <informaltable frame="all">
      <tgroup cols="2" align="left" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
        <colspec colnum="1" colname="c1" colwidth="2*"/>
        <colspec colnum="2" colname="c2" colwidth="1*"/>
        <thead>
        <row>
          <entry><para>Field</para></entry>
          <entry><para>Value</para></entry>
        </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
        <row>
          <entry><para>management.network.cidr</para></entry>
          <entry><para>A CIDR that describes the network that the management CIDRs reside on.  This 
            variable must be set for deployments that use vSphere. It is recommended to be set for 
            other deployments as well. Example: 192.168.3.0/24.</para></entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry><para>xen.setup.multipath</para></entry>
          <entry><para>For XenServer nodes, this is a true/false variable that instructs CloudStack to 
            enable iSCSI multipath on the XenServer Hosts when they are added. This defaults to false. 
            Set it to true if you would like CloudStack to enable multipath.</para>
            <para>If this is true for a NFS-based deployment multipath will still be enabled on the 
            XenServer host. However, this does not impact NFS operation and is harmless.</para></entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry><para>secstorage.allowed.internal.sites</para></entry>
          <entry><para>This is used to protect your internal network from rogue attempts to download 
            arbitrary files using the template download feature. This is a comma-separated list of CIDRs. 
            If a requested URL matches any of these CIDRs the Secondary Storage VM will use the private 
            network interface to fetch the URL. Other URLs will go through the public interface. 
            We suggest you set this to 1 or 2 hardened internal machines where you keep your templates. 
            For example, set it to 192.168.1.66/32.</para></entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry><para>use.local.storage</para></entry>
          <entry><para>Determines whether CloudStack will use storage that is local to the Host for data 
          disks, templates, and snapshots. By default CloudStack will not use this storage. You should 
          change this to true if you want to use local storage and you understand the reliability and 
          feature drawbacks to choosing local storage.</para></entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry><para>host</para></entry>
          <entry><para>This is the IP address of the Management Server. If you are using multiple 
            Management Servers you should enter a load balanced IP address that is reachable via 
            the private network.</para></entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry><para>default.page.size</para></entry>
          <entry><para>Maximum number of items per page that can be returned by a CloudStack API command. 
            The limit applies at the cloud level and can vary from cloud to cloud. You can override this 
            with a lower value on a particular API call by using the page and pagesize API command parameters. 
            For more information, see the Developer's Guide. Default: 500.</para></entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry><para>ha.tag</para></entry>
          <entry><para>The label you want to use throughout the cloud to designate certain hosts as dedicated 
            HA hosts. These hosts will be used only for HA-enabled VMs that are restarting due to the failure 
            of another host. For example, you could set this to ha_host. Specify the ha.tag value as a host tag 
            when you add a new host to the cloud.</para></entry>
        </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
  </section>
</chapter>
