<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "cloudstack.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>

<!-- Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
    or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
    distributed with this work for additional information
    regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
    to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
    "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
    with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
    software distributed under the License is distributed on an
    "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
    KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
    specific language governing permissions and limitations
    under the License.
-->
<section id="gslb">
  <title>Global Server Load Balancing Support</title>
  <para>&PRODUCT; supports Global Server Load Balancing (GSLB) functionalities to provide business
    continuity, and enable seamless resource movement within a &PRODUCT; environment. &PRODUCT;
    achieve this by extending its functionality of integrating with NetScaler Application Delivery
    Controller (ADC), which also provides various GSLB capabilities, such as disaster recovery and
    load balancing. The DNS redirection technique is used to achieve GSLB in &PRODUCT;. </para>
  <para>In order to support this functionality, region level services and service provider are
    introduced. A new service 'GSLB' is introduced as a region level service. The GSLB service
    provider is introduced that will provider the GSLB service. Currently, NetScaler is the
    supported GSLB provider in &PRODUCT;. GSLB functionality works in an Active-Active data center
    environment. </para>
  <section id="about-gslb">
    <title>About Global Server Load Balancing</title>
    <para>Global Server Load Balancing (GSLB) is an extension of load balancing functionality, which
      is highly efficient in avoiding downtime. Based on the nature of deployment, GSLB represents a
      set of technologies that is used for various purposes, such as load sharing, disaster
      recovery, performance, and legal obligations. With GSLB, workloads can be distributed across
      multiple data centers situated at geographically separated locations. GSLB can also provide an
      alternate location for accessing a resource in the event of a failure, or to provide a means
      of shifting traffic easily to simplify maintenance, or both.</para>
    <section id="gslb-comp">
      <title>Components of GSLB</title>
      <para>A typical GSLB environment is comprised of the following components:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">GSLB Site</emphasis>: In &PRODUCT; terminology, GSLB sites are
            represented by zones that are mapped to data centers, each of which has various network
            appliances. Each GSLB site is managed by a NetScaler appliance that is local to that
            site. Each of these appliances treats its own site as the local site and all other
            sites, managed by other appliances, as remote sites. It is the central entity in a GSLB
            deployment, and is represented by a name and an IP address.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">GSLB Services</emphasis>: A GSLB service is typically
            represented by a load balancing or content switching virtual server. In a GSLB
            environment, you can have a local as well as remote GSLB services. A local GSLB service
            represents a local load balancing or content switching virtual server. A remote GSLB
            service is the one configured at one of the other sites in the GSLB setup. At each site
            in the GSLB setup, you can create one local GSLB service and any number of remote GSLB
            services.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">GSLB Virtual Servers</emphasis>: A GSLB virtual server refers
            to one or more GSLB services and balances traffic between traffic across the VMs in
            multiple zones by using the &PRODUCT; functionality. It evaluates the configured GSLB
            methods or algorithms to select a GSLB service to which to send the client requests. One
            or more virtual servers from different zones are bound to the GSLB virtual server. GSLB
            virtual server does not have a public IP associated with it, instead it will have a FQDN
            DNS name.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Load Balancing or Content Switching Virtual
            Servers</emphasis>: According to Citrix NetScaler terminology, a load balancing or
            content switching virtual server represents one or many servers on the local network.
            Clients send their requests to the load balancing or content switching virtual server’s
            virtual IP (VIP) address, and the virtual server balances the load across the local
            servers. After a GSLB virtual server selects a GSLB service representing either a local
            or a remote load balancing or content switching virtual server, the client sends the
            request to that virtual server’s VIP address.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">DNS VIPs</emphasis>: DNS virtual IP represents a load
            balancing DNS virtual server on the GSLB service provider. The DNS requests for domains
            for which the GSLB service provider is authoritative can be sent to a DNS VIP.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Authoritative DNS</emphasis>: ADNS (Authoritative Domain Name
            Server) is a service that provides actual answer to DNS queries, such as web site IP
            address. In a GSLB environment, an ADNS service responds only to DNS requests for
            domains for which the GSLB service provider is authoritative. When an ADNS service is
            configured, the service provider owns that IP address and advertises it. When you create
            an ADNS service, the NetScaler responds to DNS queries on the configured ADNS service IP
            and port.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section id="concept-gslb">
      <title>How Does GSLB Works in &PRODUCT;?</title>
      <para>Global server load balancing is used to manage the traffic flow to a web site hosted on
        two separate zones that ideally are in different geographic locations. The following is an
        illustration of how GLSB functionality is provided in &PRODUCT;: An organization, xyztelco,
        has set up a public cloud that spans two zones, Zone-1 and Zone-2, across geographically
        separated data centers that are managed by &PRODUCT;. Tenant-A of the cloud launches a
        highly available solution by using xyztelco cloud. For that purpose, they launch two
        instances each in both the zones: VM1 and VM2 in Zone-1 and VM5 and VM6 in Zone-2. Tenant-A
        acquires a public IP, IP-1 in Zone-1, and configures a load balancer rule to load balance
        the traffic between VM1 and VM2 instances. &PRODUCT; orchestrates setting up a virtual
        server on the LB service provider in Zone-1. Virtual server 1 that is set up on the LB
        service provider in Zone-1 represents a publicly accessible virtual server that client
        reaches at IP-1. The client traffic to virtual server 1 at IP-1 will be load balanced across
        VM1 and VM2 instances. </para>
      <para>Tenant-A acquires another public IP, IP-2 in Zone-2 and sets up a load balancer rule to
        load balance the traffic between VM5 and VM6 instances. Similarly in Zone-2, &PRODUCT;
        orchestrates setting up a virtual server on the LB service provider. Virtual server 2 that
        is setup on the LB service provider in Zone-2 represents a publicly accessible virtual
        server that client reaches at IP-2. The client traffic that reaches virtual server 2 at IP-2
        is load balanced across VM5 and VM6 instances. At this point Tenant-A has the service
        enabled in both the zones, but has no means to set up a disaster recovery plan if one of the
        zone fails. Additionally, there is no way for Tenant-A to load balance the traffic
        intelligently to one of the zones based on load, proximity and so on. The cloud
        administrator of xyztelco provisions a GSLB service provider to both the zones. A GSLB
        provider is typically an ADC that has the ability to act as an ADNS (Authoritative Domain
        Name Server) and has the mechanism to monitor health of virtual servers both at local and
        remote sites. The cloud admin enables GSLB as a service to the tenants that use zones 1 and
        2. </para>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="./images/gslb.png"/>
        </imageobject>
        <textobject>
          <phrase>gslb.png: GSLB architecture</phrase>
        </textobject>
      </mediaobject>
      <para>Tenant-A wishes to leverage the GSLB service provided by the xyztelco cloud. Tenant-A
        configures a GSLB rule to load balance traffic across virtual server 1 at Zone-1 and virtual
        server 2 at Zone-2. The domain name is provided as A.xyztelco.com. &PRODUCT; orchestrates
        setting up GSLB virtual server 1 on the GSLB service provider at Zone-1. &PRODUCT; binds
        virtual server 1 of Zone-1 and virtual server 2 of Zone-2 to GLSB virtual server 1. GSLB
        virtual server 1 is configured to start monitoring the health of virtual server 1 and 2 in
        Zone-1. &PRODUCT; will also orchestrate setting up GSLB virtual server 2 on GSLB service
        provider at Zone-2. &PRODUCT; will bind virtual server 1 of Zone-1 and virtual server 2 of
        Zone-2 to GLSB virtual server 2. GSLB virtual server 2 is configured to start monitoring the
        health of virtual server 1 and 2. &PRODUCT; will bind the domain A.xyztelco.com to both the
        GSLB virtual server 1 and 2. At this point, Tenant-A service will be globally reachable at
        A.xyztelco.com. The private DNS server for the domain xyztelcom.com is configured by the
        admin out-of-band to resolve the domain A.xyztelco.com to the GSLB providers at both the
        zones, which are configured as ADNS for the domain A.xyztelco.com. A client when sends a DNS
        request to resolve A.xyztelcom.com, will eventually get DNS delegation to the address of
        GSLB providers at zone 1 and 2. A client DNS request will be received by the GSLB provider.
        The GSLB provider, depending on the domain for which it needs to resolve, will pick up the
        GSLB virtual server associated with the domain. Depending on the health of the virtual
        servers being load balanced, DNS request for the domain will be resolved to the public IP
        associated with the selected virtual server.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section id="gslb-workflow">
    <title>Configuring GSLB</title>
    <para>To configure a GSLB deployment, you must first configure a standard load balancing setup
      for each zone. This enables you to balance load across the different servers in each zone in
      the region. Then on the NetScaler side, configure both NetScaler appliances that you plan to
      add to each zone as authoritative DNS (ADNS) servers. Next, create a GSLB site for each zone,
      configure GSLB virtual servers for each site, create GLSB services, and bind the GSLB services
      to the GSLB virtual servers. Finally, bind the domain to the GSLB virtual servers. The GSLB
      configurations on the two appliances at the two different zones are identical, although each
      sites load-balancing configuration is specific to that site.</para>
    <para>Perform the following as a cloud administrator. As per the example given above, the
      administrator of xyztelco is the one who sets up GSLB:</para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>In the cloud.dns.name global parameter, specify the DNS name of your tenant's cloud
          that make use of the GSLB service.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>On the NetScaler side, configure GSLB as given in <ulink
            url="http://support.citrix.com/proddocs/topic/netscaler-traffic-management-10-map/ns-gslb-config-con.html"
            >Configuring Global Server Load Balancing (GSLB)</ulink>:</para>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Configuring a standard load balancing setup.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Configure Authoritative DNS, as explained in <ulink
                url="http://support.citrix.com/proddocs/topic/netscaler-traffic-management-10-map/ns-gslb-config-adns-svc-tsk.html"
                >Configuring an Authoritative DNS Service</ulink>.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Configure a GSLB site with site name formed from the domain name details.</para>
            <para>Configure a GSLB site with the site name formed from the domain name.</para>
            <para>As per the example given above, the site names are A.xyztelco.com and
              B.xyztelco.com.</para>
            <para>For more information, see <ulink
                url="http://support.citrix.com/proddocs/topic/netscaler-traffic-management-10-map/ns-gslb-config-basic-site-tsk.html"
                >Configuring a Basic GSLB Site</ulink>.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Configure a GSLB virtual server.</para>
            <para>For more information, see <ulink
                url="http://support.citrix.com/proddocs/topic/netscaler-traffic-management-10-map/ns-gslb-config-vsvr-tsk.html"
                >Configuring a GSLB Virtual Server</ulink>.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Configure a GSLB service for each virtual server.</para>
            <para>For more information, see <ulink
                url="http://support.citrix.com/proddocs/topic/netscaler-traffic-management-10-map/ns-gslb-config-svc-tsk.html"
                >Configuring a GSLB Service</ulink>.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Bind the GSLB services to the GSLB virtual server.</para>
            <para>For more information, see <ulink
                url="http://support.citrix.com/proddocs/topic/netscaler-traffic-management-10-map/ns-gslb-bind-svc-vsvr-tsk.html"
                >Binding GSLB Services to a GSLB Virtual Server</ulink>.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Bind domain name to GSLB virtual server. Domain name is obtained from the domain
              details.</para>
            <para>For more information, see <ulink
                url="http://support.citrix.com/proddocs/topic/netscaler-traffic-management-10-map/ns-gslb-bind-dom-vsvr-tsk.html"
                >Binding a Domain to a GSLB Virtual Server</ulink>.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>In each zone that are participating in GSLB, add GSLB-enabled NetScaler device.</para>
        <para>For more information, see <xref linkend="enable-glsb-ns"/>.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <para>As a domain administrator/ user perform the following:</para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Add a GSLB rule on both the sites.</para>
        <para>See <xref linkend="gslb-add"/>.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Assign load balancer rules.</para>
        <para>See <xref linkend="assign-lb-gslb"/>.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <section id="prereq-gslb">
      <title>Prerequisites and Guidelines</title>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The GSLB functionality is supported both Basic and Advanced zones.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>GSLB is added as a new network service.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>GSLB service provider can be added to a physical network in a zone.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>The admin is allowed to enable or disable GSLB functionality at region level.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>The admin is allowed to configure a zone as GSLB capable or enabled. </para>
          <para>A zone shall be considered as GSLB capable only if a GSLB service provider is
            provisioned in the zone.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>When users have VMs deployed in multiple availability zones which are GSLB enabled,
            they can use the GSLB functionality to load balance traffic across the VMs in multiple
            zones.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>The users can use GSLB to load balance across the VMs across zones in a region only
            if the admin has enabled GSLB in that region. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>The users can load balance traffic across the availability zones in the same region
            or different regions.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>The admin can configure DNS name for the entire cloud.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>The users can specify an unique name across the cloud for a globally load balanced
            service. The provided name is used as the domain name under the DNS name associated with
            the cloud.</para>
          <para>The user-provided name along with the admin-provided DNS name is used to produce a
            globally resolvable FQDN for the globally load balanced service of the user. For
            example, if the admin has configured xyztelco.com as the DNS name for the cloud, and
            user specifies 'foo' for the GSLB virtual service, then the FQDN name of the GSLB
            virtual service is foo.xyztelco.com.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>While setting up GSLB, users can select a load balancing method, such as round
            robin, for using across the zones that are part of GSLB.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>The user shall be able to set weight to zone-level virtual server. Weight shall be
            considered by the load balancing method for distributing the traffic.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>The GSLB functionality shall support session persistence, where series of client
            requests for particular domain name is sent to a virtual server on the same zone. </para>
          <para>Statistics is collected from each GSLB virtual server.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section id="enable-glsb-ns">
      <title>Enabling GSLB in NetScaler</title>
      <para>In each zone, add GSLB-enabled NetScaler device for load balancing.</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Log in as administrator to the &PRODUCT; UI.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>In the left navigation bar, click Infrastructure.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>In Zones, click View More.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Choose the zone you want to work with.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Click the Physical Network tab, then click the name of the physical network. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>In the Network Service Providers node of the diagram, click Configure. </para>
          <para>You might have to scroll down to see this.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Click NetScaler.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Click Add NetScaler device and provide the following:</para>
          <para>For NetScaler:</para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">IP Address</emphasis>: The IP address of the SRX.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Username/Password</emphasis>: The authentication
                credentials to access the device. &PRODUCT; uses these credentials to access the
                device.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Type</emphasis>: The type of device that is being added.
                It could be F5 Big Ip Load Balancer, NetScaler VPX, NetScaler MPX, or NetScaler SDX.
                For a comparison of the NetScaler types, see the &PRODUCT; Administration
                Guide.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Public interface</emphasis>: Interface of device that is
                configured to be part of the public network.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Private interface</emphasis>: Interface of device that is
                configured to be part of the private network.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">GSLB service</emphasis>: Select this option.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">GSLB service Public IP</emphasis>: The public IP address
                of the NAT translator for a GSLB service that is on a private network.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">GSLB service Private IP</emphasis>: The private IP of the
                GSLB service.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Number of Retries</emphasis>. Number of times to attempt a
                command on the device before considering the operation failed. Default is 2.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Capacity</emphasis>: The number of networks the device can
                handle.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Dedicated</emphasis>: When marked as dedicated, this
                device will be dedicated to a single account. When Dedicated is checked, the value
                in the Capacity field has no significance implicitly, its value is 1.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Click OK.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>
    <section id="gslb-add">
      <title>Adding a GSLB Rule</title>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Log in to the &PRODUCT; UI as a domain administrator or user.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>In the left navigation pane, click Region.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Select the region for which you want to create a GSLB rule.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>In the Details tab, click View GSLB.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Click Add GSLB.</para>
          <para>The Add GSLB page is displayed as follows:</para>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="./images/add-gslb.png"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>gslb-add.png: adding a gslb rule</phrase>
            </textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Specify the following:</para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Name</emphasis>: Name for the GSLB rule.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis>: (Optional) A short description of
                the GSLB rule that can be displayed to users.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">GSLB Domain Name</emphasis>: A preferred domain name for
                the service.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Algorithm</emphasis>: (Optional) The algorithm to use to
                load balance the traffic across the zones. The options are Round Robin, Least
                Connection, and Proximity.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Service Type</emphasis>: The transport protocol to use for
                GSLB. The options are TCP and UDP.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Domain</emphasis>: (Optional) The domain for which you
                want to create the GSLB rule.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Account</emphasis>: (Optional) The account on which you
                want to apply the GSLB rule.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Click OK to confirm.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>
    <section id="assign-lb-gslb">
      <title>Assigning Load Balancing Rules to GSLB</title>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Log in to the &PRODUCT; UI as a domain administrator or user.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>In the left navigation pane, click Region.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Select the region for which you want to create a GSLB rule.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>In the Details tab, click View GSLB.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Select the desired GSLB.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Click view assigned load balancing.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Click assign more load balancing.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Select the load balancing rule you have created for the zone.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Click OK to confirm.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Known Limitation</title>
    <para>Currently, &PRODUCT; does not support orchestration of services across the zones. The
      notion of services and service providers in region are to be introduced.</para>
  </section>
</section>
