<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "cloudstack.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>

<!-- Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
	or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
	distributed with this work for additional information
	regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
	to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
	"License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
	with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
	
	http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
	
	Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
	software distributed under the License is distributed on an
	"AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
	KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
	specific language governing permissions and limitations
	under the License.
-->
<section id="guest-traffic">
	<title>Guest Traffic</title>
    <para>A network can carry guest traffic only between VMs within one zone. Virtual machines in different zones cannot communicate with each other using their IP addresses; they must communicate with each other by routing through a public IP address.</para>
    <para>This figure illustrates a typical guest traffic setup:</para>
    <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="./images/guest-traffic-setup.png" />
        </imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>Depicts a guest traffic setup.</phrase></textobject>
    </mediaobject>
	<para>The Management Server automatically creates a virtual router for each network. A virtual router is a special virtual machine that runs on the hosts. Each virtual router has three network interfaces. Its eth0 interface serves as the gateway for the guest traffic and has the IP address of 10.1.1.1. Its eth1 interface is used by the system to configure the virtual router. Its eth2 interface is assigned a public IP address for public traffic.</para>
	<para>The virtual router provides DHCP and will automatically assign an IP address for each guest VM within the IP range assigned for the network. The user can manually reconfigure guest VMs to assume different IP addresses.</para>
	<para>Source NAT is automatically configured in the virtual router to forward outbound traffic for all guest VMs</para>
</section>
