<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "cloudstack.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<!-- Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
  or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
  distributed with this work for additional information
  regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
  to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
  "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
  with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
  http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
  software distributed under the License is distributed on an
  "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
  KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
  specific language governing permissions and limitations
  under the License.
-->
<section id="guest-nw-usage-with-traffic-sentinel">
  <title>Guest Network Usage Integration for Traffic Sentinel</title>
  <para>To collect usage data for a guest network, &PRODUCT; needs to pull the data from an external
    network statistics collector installed on the network. Metering statistics for guest networks
    are available through &PRODUCT;’s integration with inMon Traffic Sentinel.</para>
  <para>Traffic Sentinel is a network traffic usage data collection package. &PRODUCT; can feed
    statistics from Traffic Sentinel into its own usage records, providing a basis for billing users
    of cloud infrastructure. Traffic Sentinel uses the traffic monitoring protocol sFlow. Routers
    and switches generate sFlow records and provide them for collection by Traffic Sentinel, then
    &PRODUCT; queries the Traffic Sentinel database to obtain this information</para>
  <para>To construct the query, &PRODUCT; determines what guest IPs were in use during the current
    query interval. This includes both newly assigned IPs and IPs that were assigned in a previous
    time period and continued to be in use. &PRODUCT; queries Traffic Sentinel for network
    statistics that apply to these IPs during the time period they remained allocated in &PRODUCT;.
    The returned data is correlated with the customer account that owned each IP and the timestamps
    when IPs were assigned and released in order to create billable metering records in &PRODUCT;.
    When the Usage Server runs, it collects this data.</para>
  <para>To set up the integration between &PRODUCT; and Traffic Sentinel:</para>
  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>On your network infrastructure, install Traffic Sentinel and configure it to gather
        traffic data. For installation and configuration steps, see inMon documentation at <ulink
          url="http://inmon.com.">Traffic Sentinel Documentation</ulink>.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>In the Traffic Sentinel UI, configure Traffic Sentinel to accept script querying from
        guest users. &PRODUCT; will be the guest user performing the remote queries to gather
        network usage for one or more IP addresses.</para>
      <para>Click File > Users > Access Control > Reports Query, then select Guest from the
        drop-down list.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>On &PRODUCT;, add the Traffic Sentinel host by calling the &PRODUCT; API command
        addTrafficMonitor. Pass in the URL of the Traffic Sentinel as protocol + host + port
        (optional); for example, http://10.147.28.100:8080. For the addTrafficMonitor command
        syntax, see the API Reference at <ulink
            url="http://cloudstack.apache.org/docs/api/index.html">API
        Documentation</ulink>.</para>
      <para>For information about how to call the &PRODUCT; API, see the Developer’s Guide at
          <ulink url="http://cloudstack.apache.org/docs/en-US/index.html">
              &PRODUCT; API Developer's Guide</ulink>.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Log in to the &PRODUCT; UI as administrator.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Select Configuration from the Global Settings page, and set the following:</para>
      <para>direct.network.stats.interval: How often you want &PRODUCT; to query Traffic
        Sentinel.</para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
</section>
