<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "cloudstack.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>

<!-- Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
    or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
    distributed with this work for additional information
    regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
    to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
    "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
    with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
    
    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
    
    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
    software distributed under the License is distributed on an
    "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
    KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
    specific language governing permissions and limitations
    under the License.
-->
<section id="host-add-xenserver-kvm-ovm">
  <title>Adding a Host (XenServer or KVM)</title>
  <para>XenServer and KVM hosts can be added to a cluster at any time.</para>
  <section>
    <title>Requirements for XenServer and KVM Hosts</title>
    <warning>
      <para>Make sure the hypervisor host does not have any VMs already running before you add it to
        &PRODUCT;.</para>
    </warning>
    <para>Configuration requirements:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Each cluster must contain only hosts with the identical hypervisor. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>For XenServer, do not put more than 8 hosts in a cluster. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>For KVM, do not put more than 16 hosts in a cluster.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>For hardware requirements, see the installation section for your hypervisor in the
      &PRODUCT; Installation Guide.</para>
    <section>
      <title>XenServer Host Additional Requirements</title>
      <para>If network bonding is in use, the administrator must cable the new host identically to
        other hosts in the cluster. </para>
      <para>For all additional hosts to be added to the cluster, run the following command. This
        will cause the host to join the master in a XenServer pool. </para>
      <programlisting># xe pool-join master-address=[master IP] master-username=root master-password=[your password]</programlisting>
      <note>
        <para>When copying and pasting a command, be sure the command has pasted as a single line
          before executing. Some document viewers may introduce unwanted line breaks in copied
          text.</para>
      </note>
      <para>With all hosts added to the XenServer pool, run the cloud-setup-bond script. This script
        will complete the configuration and setup of the bonds on the new hosts in the
        cluster.</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Copy the script from the Management Server in
            /usr/share/cloudstack-common/scripts/vm/hypervisor/xenserver/cloud-setup-bonding.sh to the
            master host and ensure it is executable.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Run the script:</para>
          <programlisting># ./cloud-setup-bonding.sh</programlisting>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>KVM Host Additional Requirements</title>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>If shared mountpoint storage is in use, the administrator should ensure that the new
            host has all the same mountpoints (with storage mounted) as the other hosts in the
            cluster.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Make sure the new host has the same network configuration (guest, private, and
            public network) as other hosts in the cluster.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>If you are using OpenVswitch bridges edit the file agent.properties on the KVM host
            and set the parameter <emphasis role="italic">network.bridge.type</emphasis> to
              <emphasis role="italic">openvswitch</emphasis> before adding the host to &PRODUCT;</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <!-- <section>
    <title>OVM Host Additional Requirements</title>
      <para>Before adding a used host in &PRODUCT;, as part of the cleanup procedure on the host, be
          sure to remove /etc/ovs-agent/db/.</para> 
    </section> -->
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Adding a XenServer or KVM Host</title>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>If you have not already done so, install the hypervisor software on the host. You will
          need to know which version of the hypervisor software version is supported by &PRODUCT;
          and what additional configuration is required to ensure the host will work with &PRODUCT;.
          To find these installation details, see the appropriate section for your hypervisor in the
          &PRODUCT; Installation Guide.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Log in to the &PRODUCT; UI as administrator.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>In the left navigation, choose Infrastructure. In Zones, click View More, then click
          the zone in which you want to add the host.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Click the Compute tab. In the Clusters node, click View All.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Click the cluster where you want to add the host.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Click View Hosts.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Click Add Host.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Provide the following information.</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Host Name. The DNS name or IP address of the host.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Username. Usually root.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Password. This is the password for the user from your XenServer or KVM
              install).</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Host Tags (Optional). Any labels that you use to categorize hosts for ease of
              maintenance. For example, you can set to the cloud's HA tag (set in the ha.tag global
              configuration parameter) if you want this host to be used only for VMs with the "high
              availability" feature enabled. For more information, see HA-Enabled Virtual Machines
              as well as HA for Hosts.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>There may be a slight delay while the host is provisioned. It should automatically
          display in the UI. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Repeat for additional hosts. </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
</section>
