<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "file:///C:/Program%20Files%20(x86)/Publican/DocBook_DTD/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "cloudstack.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<section id="install-management-server">
	<title>Install the Management Server on the First Host</title>
	<para>The first step in installation, whether you are installing the Management Server on one host or many, is to
		install the software on a single node.
	</para>
	<note><para>If you are planning to install the Management Server on multiple nodes
		for high availability, do not proceed to the additional nodes yet. That step will come later.</para></note>
	<orderedlist>
		<listitem><para>Download the Management Server onto the host where it will run.
			Get the software from the following link.</para>
			<para><ulink url="https://www.citrix.com/English/ss/downloads/">https://www.citrix.com/English/ss/downloads/</ulink></para>
			<para>You will need a <ulink url="http://www.citrix.com/lang/English/publicindex.asp?destURL=%2FEnglish%2FmyCitrix%2Findex.asp%3F">MyCitrix account</ulink>.</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem><para>Install the  packages. You should have a file in the form of “&PRODUCT;-VERSION-N-OSVERSION.tar.gz”. Untar the file and then run the install.sh script inside it. Replace the file and directory names below with those you are using:</para>
			<programlisting>
# tar xzf &PRODUCT;-VERSION-N-OSVERSION.tar.gz
# cd &PRODUCT;-VERSION-N-OSVERSION
# ./install.sh
			</programlisting>
			<para>You should see a few messages as the installer prepares, followed by a list of choices.</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem><para>Choose M to install the Management Server software.</para>
			<programlisting>  > M</programlisting>
		</listitem>
		<listitem><para>Wait for a message like “Complete! Done,” which indicates that the software was installed successfully.</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem><para>(RHEL or CentOS) When the installation is finished, run the following commands to start essential services  (the commands might be different depending on your OS):</para>
			<programlisting>
# service rpcbind start
# service nfs start
# chkconfig nfs on
# chkconfig rpcbind on
			</programlisting>
		</listitem>
	</orderedlist>
</section>
