<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "cloudstack.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>

<!-- Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
    or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
    distributed with this work for additional information
    regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
    to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
    "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
    with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
    
    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
    
    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
    software distributed under the License is distributed on an
    "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
    KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
    specific language governing permissions and limitations
    under the License.
-->
<section id="network-offerings">
  <title>Network Offerings</title>
  <note>
    <para>For the most up-to-date list of supported network services, see the &PRODUCT; UI or call
      listNetworkServices.</para>
  </note>
  <para>A network offering is a named set of network services, such as:</para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>DHCP</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>DNS</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Source NAT</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Static NAT</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Port Forwarding</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Load Balancing</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Firewall</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>VPN</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>(Optional) Name one of several available providers to use for a given service, such as
        Juniper for the firewall</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>(Optional) Network tag to specify which physical network to use</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>When creating a new VM, the user chooses one of the available network offerings, and that
    determines which network services the VM can use.</para>
  <para>The &PRODUCT; administrator can create any number of custom network offerings, in addition
    to the default network offerings provided by &PRODUCT;. By creating multiple custom network
    offerings, you can set up your cloud to offer different classes of service on a single
    multi-tenant physical network. For example, while the underlying physical wiring may be the same
    for two tenants, tenant A may only need simple firewall protection for their website, while
    tenant B may be running a web server farm and require a scalable firewall solution, load
    balancing solution, and alternate networks for accessing the database backend.</para>
  <note>
    <para>If you create load balancing rules while using a network service offering that includes an
      external load balancer device such as NetScaler, and later change the network service offering
      to one that uses the &PRODUCT; virtual router, you must create a firewall rule on the virtual
      router for each of your existing load balancing rules so that they continue to
      function.</para>
  </note>
  <para>When creating a new virtual network, the &PRODUCT; administrator chooses which network
    offering to enable for that network. Each virtual network is associated with one network
    offering. A virtual network can be upgraded or downgraded by changing its associated network
    offering. If you do this, be sure to reprogram the physical network to match.</para>
  <para>&PRODUCT; also has internal network offerings for use by &PRODUCT; system VMs. These network
    offerings are not visible to users but can be modified by administrators.</para>
  <xi:include href="creating-network-offerings.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
</section>
