<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "cloudstack.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>

<!-- Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
 or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
 distributed with this work for additional information
 regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
 to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
 "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
 with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
   http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
 Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
 software distributed under the License is distributed on an
 "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
 KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
 specific language governing permissions and limitations
 under the License.
-->
<section id="pvlan">
  <title>Isolation in Advanced Zone Using Private VLAN</title>
  <para>Isolation of guest traffic in shared networks can be achieved by using Private VLANs
    (PVLAN). PVLANs provide Layer 2 isolation between ports within the same VLAN. In a PVLAN-enabled
    shared network, a user VM cannot reach other user VM though they can reach the DHCP server and
    gateway, this would in turn allow users to control traffic within a network and help them deploy
    multiple applications without communication between application as well as prevent communication
    with other users’ VMs.</para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Isolate VMs in a shared networks by using Private VLANs.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Supported on KVM, XenServer, and VMware hypervisors</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>PVLAN-enabled shared network can be a part of multiple networks of a guest VM.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <section id="about-pvlan">
    <title>About Private VLAN</title>
    <para>In an Ethernet switch, a VLAN is a broadcast domain where hosts can establish direct
      communication with each another at Layer 2. Private VLAN is designed as an extension of VLAN
      standard to add further segmentation of the logical broadcast domain. A regular VLAN is a
      single broadcast domain, whereas a private VLAN partitions a larger VLAN broadcast domain into
      smaller sub-domains. A sub-domain is represented by a pair of VLANs: a Primary VLAN and a
      Secondary VLAN. The original VLAN that is being divided into smaller groups is called Primary,
      which implies that all VLAN pairs in a private VLAN share the same Primary VLAN. All the
      secondary VLANs exist only inside the Primary. Each Secondary VLAN has a specific VLAN ID
      associated to it, which differentiates one sub-domain from another. </para>
    <para>Three types of ports exist in a private VLAN domain, which essentially determine the
      behaviour of the participating hosts. Each ports will have its own unique set of rules, which
      regulate a connected host's ability to communicate with other connected host within the same
      private VLAN domain. Configure each host that is part of a PVLAN pair can be by using one of
      these three port designation:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Promiscuous</emphasis>: A promiscuous port can communicate with
          all the interfaces, including the community and isolated host ports that belong to the
          secondary VLANs. In Promiscuous mode, hosts are connected to promiscuous ports and are
          able to communicate directly with resources on both primary and secondary VLAN. Routers,
          DHCP servers, and other trusted devices are typically attached to promiscuous
          ports.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Isolated VLANs</emphasis>: The ports within an isolated VLAN
          cannot communicate with each other at the layer-2 level. The hosts that are connected to
          Isolated ports can directly communicate only with the Promiscuous resources. If your
          customer device needs to have access only to a gateway router, attach it to an isolated
          port.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Community VLANs</emphasis>: The ports within a community VLAN
          can communicate with each other and with the promiscuous ports, but they cannot
          communicate with the ports in other communities at the layer-2 level. In a Community mode,
          direct communication is permitted only with the hosts in the same community and those that
          are connected to the Primary PVLAN in promiscuous mode. If your customer has two devices
          that need to be isolated from other customers' devices, but to be able to communicate
          among themselves, deploy them in community ports.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>For further reading:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><ulink
            url="http://www.cisco.com/en/US/docs/switches/lan/catalyst3750/software/release/12.2_25_see/configuration/guide/swpvlan.html#wp1038379"
            >Understanding Private VLANs</ulink></para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><ulink url="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc5517">Cisco Systems' Private VLANs: Scalable
            Security in a Multi-Client Environment</ulink></para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><ulink url="http://kb.vmware.com">Private VLAN (PVLAN) on vNetwork Distributed Switch
            - Concept Overview (1010691)</ulink></para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section id="prereq-pvlan">
    <title>Prerequisites</title>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Use a PVLAN supported switch.</para>
        <para>See <ulink
            url="http://www.cisco.com/en/US/products/hw/switches/ps708/products_tech_note09186a0080094830.shtml"
            >Private VLAN Catalyst Switch Support Matrix</ulink>for more information.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>All the layer 2 switches, which are PVLAN-aware, are connected to each other, and one
          of them is connected to a router. All the ports connected to the host would be configured
          in trunk mode. Open Management VLAN, Primary VLAN (public) and Secondary Isolated VLAN
          ports. Configure the switch port connected to the router in PVLAN promiscuous trunk mode,
          which would translate an isolated VLAN to primary VLAN for the PVLAN-unaware router. </para>
        <para>Note that only Cisco Catalyst 4500 has the PVLAN promiscuous trunk mode to connect
          both normal VLAN and PVLAN to a PVLAN-unaware switch. For the other Catalyst PVLAN support
          switch, connect the switch to upper switch by using cables, one each for a PVLAN
          pair.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Configure private VLAN on your physical switches out-of-band.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Before you use PVLAN on XenServer and KVM, enable Open vSwitch (OVS).</para>
        <note>
          <para>OVS on XenServer and KVM does not support PVLAN natively. Therefore, &PRODUCT;
            managed to simulate PVLAN on OVS for XenServer and KVM by modifying the flow
            table.</para>
        </note>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section id="ability-pvlan">
    <title>Creating a PVLAN-Enabled Guest Network</title>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Log in to the &PRODUCT; UI as administrator.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>In the left navigation, choose Infrastructure.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>On Zones, click View More.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Click the zone to which you want to add a guest network.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Click the Physical Network tab.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Click the physical network you want to work with.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>On the Guest node of the diagram, click Configure.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Click the Network tab.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Click Add guest network.</para>
        <para>The Add guest network window is displayed.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Specify the following:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Name</emphasis>: The name of the network. This will be
              visible to the user.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis>: The short description of the network
              that can be displayed to users.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">VLAN ID</emphasis>: The unique ID of the VLAN.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Secondary Isolated VLAN ID</emphasis>: The unique ID of the
              Secondary Isolated VLAN. </para>
            <para>For the description on Secondary Isolated VLAN, see <xref linkend="about-pvlan"
              />.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Scope</emphasis>: The available scopes are Domain, Account,
              Project, and All.</para>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Domain</emphasis>: Selecting Domain limits the scope of
                  this guest network to the domain you specify. The network will not be available
                  for other domains. If you select Subdomain Access, the guest network is available
                  to all the sub domains within the selected domain.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Account</emphasis>: The account for which the guest
                  network is being created for. You must specify the domain the account belongs
                  to.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Project</emphasis>: The project for which the guest
                  network is being created for. You must specify the domain the project belongs
                  to.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">All</emphasis>: The guest network is available for all
                  the domains, account, projects within the selected zone. </para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Network Offering</emphasis>: If the administrator has
              configured multiple network offerings, select the one you want to use for this
              network.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Gateway</emphasis>: The gateway that the guests should
              use.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Netmask</emphasis>: The netmask in use on the subnet the
              guests will use.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">IP Range</emphasis>: A range of IP addresses that are
              accessible from the Internet and are assigned to the guest VMs.</para>
            <!--<para>If one NIC is used, these IPs should be in the same CIDR in the case of
              IPv6.</para> -->
          </listitem>
          <!-- <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">IPv6 CIDR</emphasis>: The network prefix that defines the
              guest network subnet. This is the CIDR that describes the IPv6 addresses in use in the
              guest networks in this zone. To allot IP addresses from within a particular address
              block, enter a CIDR.</para>
          </listitem> -->
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Network Domain</emphasis>: A custom DNS suffix at the level
              of a network. If you want to assign a special domain name to the guest VM network,
              specify a DNS suffix.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Click OK to confirm.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
</section>
