<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "cloudstack.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>

<!-- Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
 or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
 distributed with this work for additional information
 regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
 to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
 "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
 with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
 
   http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
 
 Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
 software distributed under the License is distributed on an
 "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
 KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
 specific language governing permissions and limitations
 under the License.
-->
<section id="sticky-session-policies-for-lb-rules">
  <title>Sticky Session Policies for Load Balancer Rules</title>
  <para>Sticky sessions are used in Web-based applications to ensure continued availability of
    information across the multiple requests in a user's session. For example, if a shopper is
    filling a cart, you need to remember what has been purchased so far. The concept of "stickiness"
    is also referred to as persistence or maintaining state.</para>
  <para>Any load balancer rule defined in &PRODUCT; can have a stickiness policy. The policy
    consists of a name, stickiness method, and parameters. The parameters are name-value pairs or
    flags, which are defined by the load balancer vendor. The stickiness method could be load
    balancer-generated cookie, application-generated cookie, or source-based. In the source-based
    method, the source IP address is used to identify the user and locate the user’s stored data. In
    the other methods, cookies are used. The cookie generated by the load balancer or application is
    included in request and response URLs to create persistence. The cookie name can be specified by
    the administrator or automatically generated. A variety of options are provided to control the
    exact behavior of cookies, such as how they are generated and whether they are cached.</para>
  <para>For the most up to date list of available stickiness methods, see the &PRODUCT; UI or call
    listNetworks and check the SupportedStickinessMethods capability.</para>
</section>
