<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "cloudstack.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>

<!-- Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
 or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
 distributed with this work for additional information
 regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
 to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
 "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
 with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
 
   http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
 
 Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
 software distributed under the License is distributed on an
 "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
 KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
 specific language governing permissions and limitations
 under the License.
-->

<section id="using-swift-for-secondary-storage">
    <title>Using Swift for Secondary Storage</title>
    <para>&PRODUCT; supports OpenStack Object Storage (<ulink url="http://swift.openstack.org/"> Swift</ulink>) for secondary storage. When using Swift, you configure Swift storage for the entire &PRODUCT;, then set up NFS secondary storage for each zone as usual. The NFS storage in each zone acts as a staging area through which all templates and other secondary storage data pass before being forwarded to Swift. The Swift storage acts as a cloud-wide resource, making templates and other data available to any zone in the cloud. There is no hierarchy in the Swift storage, just one Swift container per storage object. Any secondary storage in the whole cloud can pull a container from Swift at need. It is not necessary to copy templates and snapshots from one zone to another, as would be required when using zone NFS alone. Everything is available everywhere</para>
    <para>Swift storage must be set up before you add NFS secondary storage to zones. This is accomplished through some additional configuration steps on a fresh Management Server installation, before you add the first zone. The procedure is described in Adding a Zone in the Advanced Installation Guide.</para>
</section>
