<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "cloudstack.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>

<!-- Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
 or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
 distributed with this work for additional information
 regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
 to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
 "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
 with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
 
   http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
 
 Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
 software distributed under the License is distributed on an
 "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
 KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
 specific language governing permissions and limitations
 under the License.
-->
<section id="vlan-provisioning">
  <title>VLAN Provisioning</title>
  <para>&PRODUCT; automatically creates and destroys interfaces bridged to VLANs on the hosts. In
    general the administrator does not need to manage this process.</para>
  <para>&PRODUCT; manages VLANs differently based on hypervisor type. For XenServer or KVM, the
    VLANs are created on only the hosts where they will be used and then they are destroyed when all
    guests that require them have been terminated or moved to another host.</para>
  <para>For vSphere the VLANs are provisioned on all hosts in the cluster even if there is no guest
    running on a particular Host that requires the VLAN. This allows the administrator to perform
    live migration and other functions in vCenter without having to create the VLAN on the
    destination Host. Additionally, the VLANs are not removed from the Hosts when they are no longer
    needed.</para>
  <para>You can use the same VLANs on different physical networks provided that each physical
    network has its own underlying layer-2 infrastructure, such as switches. For example, you can
    specify VLAN range 500 to 1000 while deploying physical networks A and B in an Advanced zone
    setup. This capability allows you to set up an additional layer-2 physical infrastructure on a
    different physical NIC and use the same set of VLANs if you run out of VLANs. Another advantage
    is that you can use the same set of IPs for different customers, each one with their own routers
    and the guest networks on different physical NICs.</para>
  <xi:include href="vlan-allocation-eg.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
  <xi:include href="non-contiguous-vlan.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
</section>
