<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "cloudstack.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>

<!-- Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
    or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
    distributed with this work for additional information
    regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
    to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
    "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
    with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
    
    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
    
    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
    software distributed under the License is distributed on an
    "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
    KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
    specific language governing permissions and limitations
    under the License.
-->
<section id="vm-storage-migration">
  <title>VM Storage Migration</title>
  <para>Supported in XenServer, KVM, and VMware.</para>
  <note><para>This procedure is different from moving disk volumes from one VM to another as described in
    <xref linkend="detach-move-volumes"/>.</para></note>
  <para/>
  <para>You can migrate a virtual machine’s root disk volume or any additional data disk volume from one storage pool to another in the same zone.</para>
  <para>You can use the storage migration feature to achieve some commonly desired administration goals, such as balancing the load on storage pools and increasing the reliability of virtual machines by moving them away from any storage  pool that is experiencing  issues.</para>
  <para>On XenServer and VMware, live migration of VM storage is enabled through &PRODUCT;
    support for XenMotion and vMotion.
    Live storage migration allows VMs to be moved from one host to another, where the VMs are
    not located on storage shared between the two hosts. It provides the option to live
    migrate a VM’s disks along with the VM itself. It is possible to migrate a VM from one
    XenServer resource pool / VMware cluster to another, or to migrate a VM whose disks are on
    local storage, or even to migrate a VM’s disks from one storage repository to another, all
    while the VM is running.</para>
  <note><para>Because of a limitation in VMware, live migration of storage for a VM is allowed only
    if the source and target storage pool are accessible to the source host; that is, the host
    where the VM is running when the live migration operation is requested.</para></note>
  <para/>
  <xi:include href="migrate-datadisk-volume-new-storage-pool.xml"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
  <xi:include href="migrate-vm-rootvolume-volume-new-storage-pool.xml"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
</section>
