<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "cloudstack.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>

<!-- Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
 or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
 distributed with this work for additional information
 regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
 to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
 "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
 with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
 http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
 Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
 software distributed under the License is distributed on an
 "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
 KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
 specific language governing permissions and limitations
 under the License.
-->
<section id="vmware-cluster-config-dvswitch">
  <title>Configuring a vSphere Cluster with VMware Distributed Virtual Switch</title>
  <para>&PRODUCT;supports VMware vNetwork Distributed Switch (VDS) for virtual network configuration
    in a VMware vSphere environment. This section helps you configure VMware VDS in a &PRODUCT;
    deployment. Each vCenter server instance can support up to 128 VDS instances and each VDS
    instance can manage up to 500 VMware hosts.</para>
  <section id="about-dvswitch">
    <title>About VMware Distributed Virtual Switch</title>
    <para>VMware VDS is an aggregation of host-level virtual switches on a VMware vCenter server.
      VDS abstracts the configuration of individual virtual switches that span across a large number
      of hosts, and enables centralized provisioning, administration, and monitoring for your entire
      datacenter from a centralized interface. In effect, a VDS acts as a single virtual switch at
      the datacenter level and manages networking for a number of hosts in a datacenter from a
      centralized VMware vCenter server. Each VDS maintains network runtime state for VMs as they
      move across multiple hosts, enabling inline monitoring and centralized firewall services. A
      VDS can be deployed with or without Virtual Standard Switch and a Nexus 1000V virtual
      switch.</para>
  </section>
  <section id="prereq-dvswitch">
    <title>Prerequisites and Guidelines</title>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Do not attempt to configure VDS by altering VMware traffic label when configuring
          physical networks. This will only work for Standard Virtual Switch and should not be
          distributed.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>VMware VDS does not support multiple VDS per traffic type. If a user has many VDS
          switches, only one can be used for Guest traffic and another one for Public
          traffic.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Management and Storage network does not support VDS. Therefore, use Standard Switch
          for these networks.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section id="enable-dvswitch">
    <title>Enabling Virtual Distributed Switch in &PRODUCT;</title>
    <para>To make a &PRODUCT; deployment VDS enabled, set the vmware.use.dvswitch parameter to true
      by using the Global Settings page in the &PRODUCT; UI and restart the Management Server.
      Unless you enable the vmware.use.dvswitch parameter, you cannot see any UI options specific to
      VDS, and &PRODUCT; ignores the VDS-specific parameters given in the AddClusterCmd API call.
      Additionally, &PRODUCT; uses VDS for virtual network infrastructure if the value of
      vmware.use.dvswitch parameter is true and the value of vmware.use.nexus.dvswitch parameter is
      false.</para>
    <para>&PRODUCT; supports orchestration of virtual networks in a deployment with a mix of Virtual
      Distributed Switch, Standard Virtual Switch and Nexus 1000v Virtual Switch. </para>
  </section>
  <section id="config-dvswitch">
    <title>Configuring Distributed Virtual Switch in &PRODUCT;</title>
    <para>You can configure VDS by adding the necessary resources while a zone is created.</para>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="./images/dvSwitch-config.png"/>
      </imageobject>
      <textobject>
        <phrase>dvSwitchConfig.png: Configuring dvSwitch</phrase>
      </textobject>
    </mediaobject>
    <para>Alternatively, you can create an additional cluster with VDS enabled in the existing zone.
      Use the Add Cluster option. For information as given in <xref linkend="add-clusters-vsphere"
      />.</para>
    <para>In both these cases, you must specify the following parameters to configure VDS:</para>
    <informaltable frame="all">
      <tgroup cols="2" align="left" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
        <colspec colname="c1"/>
        <colspec colname="c2"/>
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry><para>Parameters</para></entry>
            <entry><para>Description</para></entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry><para>Cluster Name</para></entry>
            <entry><para>Enter the name of the cluster you created in vCenter. For example,
                &quot;cloud.cluster&quot;.</para></entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry><para>vCenter Host</para></entry>
            <entry><para>Enter the name or the IP address of the vCenter host where you have deployed the VMware
                VDS.</para></entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry><para>vCenter User name</para></entry>
            <entry><para>Enter the username that &PRODUCT; should use to connect to vCenter. This
                user must have all administrative privileges.</para></entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry><para>vCenter Password</para></entry>
            <entry><para>Enter the password for the user named above.</para></entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry><para>vCenter Datacenter</para></entry>
            <entry><para>Enter the vCenter datacenter that the cluster is in. For example,
                &quot;cloud.dc.VM&quot;.</para></entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry><para>Override Public Traffic</para></entry>
            <entry><para>Enable this option to override the zone-wide public traffic for the cluster
                you are creating. </para></entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry><para>Public Traffic vSwitch Type</para></entry>
            <entry><para>This option is displayed only if you enable the Override Public Traffic
                option. Select VMware vNetwork Distributed Virtual Switch. </para>
              <para>If the vmware.use.dvswitch global parameter is true, the default option will be
                VMware vNetwork Distributed Virtual Switch.</para></entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry><para>Public Traffic vSwitch Name</para></entry>
            <entry><para>Name of virtual switch to be used for the public traffic.</para></entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry><para>Override Guest Traffic</para></entry>
            <entry><para>Enable the option to override the zone-wide guest traffic for the cluster
                you are creating.</para></entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry><para>Guest Traffic vSwitch Type</para></entry>
            <entry><para>This option is displayed only if you enable the Override Guest Traffic
                option. Select VMware vNetwork Distributed Virtual Switch. </para>
              <para>If the vmware.use.dvswitch global parameter is true, the default option will be
                VMware vNetwork Distributed Virtual Switch.</para></entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry><para>Guest Traffic vSwitch Name</para></entry>
            <entry><para>Name of virtual switch to be used for guest traffic.</para></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
  </section>
  <section id="vmware-dvswitch-remove">
    <title>Removing VMware Virtual Switch</title>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>In the vCenter datacenter that is served by the VDS, ensure that you delete all the
          hosts in the corresponding cluster.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Log in with Admin permissions to the &PRODUCT; administrator UI.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>In the left navigation bar, select Infrastructure.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>In the Infrastructure page, click View all under Clusters.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Select the cluster where you want to remove the virtual switch.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>In the VMware dvSwitch tab, click the name of the virtual switch.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para> In the Details page, click Delete VMware dvSwitch icon. <inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="./images/delete-button.png"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>DeleteButton.png: button to delete dvSwitch</phrase>
            </textobject>
          </inlinemediaobject>
        </para>
        <para>Click Yes in the confirmation dialog box.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
</section>
