<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "cloudstack.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>

<!-- Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
 or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
 distributed with this work for additional information
 regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
 to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
 "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
 with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
 http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
 Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
 software distributed under the License is distributed on an
 "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
 KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
 specific language governing permissions and limitations
 under the License.
-->
<section id="vmware-cluster-config-dvswitch">
  <title>Configuring a VMware Datacenter with VMware Distributed Virtual Switch</title>
  <para>&PRODUCT; supports VMware vNetwork Distributed Switch (VDS) for virtual network
    configuration in a VMware vSphere environment. This section helps you configure VMware VDS in a
    &PRODUCT; deployment. Each vCenter server instance can support up to 128 VDS instances and each
    VDS instance can manage up to 500 VMware hosts.</para>
  <section id="about-dvswitch">
    <title>About VMware Distributed Virtual Switch</title>
    <para>VMware VDS is an aggregation of host-level virtual switches on a VMware vCenter server.
      VDS abstracts the configuration of individual virtual switches that span across a large number
      of hosts, and enables centralized provisioning, administration, and monitoring for your entire
      datacenter from a centralized interface. In effect, a VDS acts as a single virtual switch at
      the datacenter level and manages networking for a number of hosts in a datacenter from a
      centralized VMware vCenter server. Each VDS maintains network runtime state for VMs as they
      move across multiple hosts, enabling inline monitoring and centralized firewall services. A
      VDS can be deployed with or without Virtual Standard Switch and a Nexus 1000V virtual
      switch.</para>
  </section>
  <section id="prereq-dvswitch">
    <title>Prerequisites and Guidelines</title>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>VMware VDS is supported only on Public and Guest traffic in &PRODUCT;.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>VMware VDS does not support multiple VDS per traffic type. If a user has many VDS
          switches, only one can be used for Guest traffic and another one for Public
          traffic.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Additional switches of any type can be added for each cluster in the same zone. While
          adding the clusters with different switch type, traffic labels is overridden at the
          cluster level.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Management and Storage network does not support VDS. Therefore, use Standard Switch
          for these networks.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>When you remove a guest network, the corresponding dvportgroup will not be removed on
          the vCenter. You must manually delete them on the vCenter.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section id="preconfig-checklist-vds">
    <title>Preparation Checklist</title>
    <para>For a smoother configuration of VMware VDS, note down the VDS name you have added in the
      datacenter before you start:</para>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="./images/vds-name.png"/>
      </imageobject>
      <textobject>
        <phrase>vds-name.png: Name of the dvSwitch as specified in the vCenter.</phrase>
      </textobject>
    </mediaobject>
    <para>Use this VDS name when you specify the switch name in the traffic label while creating the
      zone. Traffic label format is [["Name of vSwitch/dvSwitch/EthernetPortProfile"][,"VLAN
      ID"[,"vSwitch Type"]]]</para>
    <para>The possible values for traffic labels are:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>empty string</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>dvSwitch0</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para> dvSwitch0,200</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>dvSwitch1,300,vmwaredvs</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>myEthernetPortProfile,,nexusdvs</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>dvSwitch0,,vmwaredvs</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="./images/traffic-label.png"/>
      </imageobject>
      <textobject>
        <phrase>traffic-label.png: Traffic label specified while zone creation.</phrase>
      </textobject>
    </mediaobject>
    <informaltable frame="all">
      <tgroup cols="3" align="left" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
        <colspec colname="c1"/>
        <colspec colname="c2"/>
        <colspec colname="c3"/>
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry><para>Fields</para></entry>
            <entry><para>Name</para></entry>
            <entry><para>Description</para></entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry><para>1</para></entry>
            <entry><para>Represents the name of the virtual / distributed virtual switch at
                vCenter.</para></entry>
            <entry><para>The default value depends on the type of virtual switch:</para>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">vSwitch0</emphasis>: If type of virtual switch is VMware
                vNetwork Standard virtual switch </para>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">dvSwitch0</emphasis>: If type of virtual switch is VMware
                vNetwork Distributed virtual switch</para>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">epp0</emphasis>: If type of virtual switch is Cisco Nexus
                1000v Distributed virtual switch</para></entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry><para>2</para></entry>
            <entry><para>VLAN ID to be used for this traffic wherever applicable.</para></entry>
            <entry><para>This field would be used for only public traffic as of now. In case of guest traffic this
                field would be ignored and could be left empty for guest traffic. By default empty
                string would be assumed which translates to untagged VLAN for that specific traffic
                type.</para></entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry><para>3</para></entry>
            <entry><para>Type of virtual switch. Specified as string.</para></entry>
            <entry><para>Possible valid values are vmwaredvs, vmwaresvs, nexusdvs. </para>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">vmwaresvs</emphasis>: Represents VMware vNetwork Standard
                virtual switch</para>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">vmwaredvs</emphasis>: Represents VMware vNetwork
                distributed virtual switch</para>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">nexusdvs</emphasis>: Represents Cisco Nexus 1000v
                distributed virtual switch.</para>
              <para>If nothing specified (left empty), zone-level default virtual switch would be
                defaulted, based on the value of global parameter you specify. </para>
              <para>Following are the global configuration parameters:</para>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">vmware.use.dvswitch</emphasis>: Set to true to enable any
                kind (VMware DVS and Cisco Nexus 1000v) of distributed virtual switch in a &PRODUCT;
                deployment. If set to false, the virtual switch that can be used in that &PRODUCT;
                deployment is Standard virtual switch. </para>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">vmware.use.nexus.vswitch</emphasis>: This parameter is
                ignored if vmware.use.dvswitch is set to false. Set to true to enable Cisco Nexus
                1000v distributed virtual switch in a &PRODUCT; deployment.</para></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
  </section>
  <section id="enable-dvswitch">
    <title>Enabling Virtual Distributed Switch in &PRODUCT;</title>
    <para>To make a &PRODUCT; deployment VDS enabled, set the vmware.use.dvswitch parameter to true
      by using the Global Settings page in the &PRODUCT; UI and restart the Management Server.
      Unless you enable the vmware.use.dvswitch parameter, you cannot see any UI options specific to
      VDS, and &PRODUCT; ignores the VDS-specific parameters that you specify. Additionally,
      &PRODUCT; uses VDS for virtual network infrastructure if the value of vmware.use.dvswitch
      parameter is true and the value of vmware.use.nexus.dvswitch parameter is false. Another
      global parameter that defines VDS configuration is vmware.ports.per.dvportgroup. This is the
      default number of ports per VMware dvPortGroup in a VMware environment. Default value is 256.
      This number directly associated with the number of guest network you can create.</para>
    <para>&PRODUCT; supports orchestration of virtual networks in a deployment with a mix of Virtual
      Distributed Switch, Standard Virtual Switch and Nexus 1000v Virtual Switch. </para>
  </section>
  <section id="config-dvswitch">
    <title>Configuring Distributed Virtual Switch in &PRODUCT;</title>
    <para>You can configure VDS by adding the necessary resources while a zone is created.</para>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="./images/dvSwitch-config.png"/>
      </imageobject>
      <textobject>
        <phrase>dvSwitchConfig.png: Configuring dvSwitch</phrase>
      </textobject>
    </mediaobject>
    <para>Alternatively, you can create an additional cluster with VDS enabled in the existing zone.
      Use the Add Cluster option. For information as given in <xref linkend="add-clusters-vsphere"
      />.</para>
    <para>In both these cases, you must specify the following parameters to configure VDS:</para>
    <informaltable frame="all">
      <tgroup cols="2" align="left" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
        <colspec colname="c1"/>
        <colspec colname="c2"/>
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry><para>Parameters</para></entry>
            <entry><para>Description</para></entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry><para>Cluster Name</para></entry>
            <entry><para>Enter the name of the cluster you created in vCenter. For example,
                &quot;cloudcluster&quot;.</para></entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry><para>vCenter Host</para></entry>
            <entry><para>Enter the name or the IP address of the vCenter host where you have
                deployed the VMware VDS.</para></entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry><para>vCenter User name</para></entry>
            <entry><para>Enter the username that &PRODUCT; should use to connect to vCenter. This
                user must have all administrative privileges.</para></entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry><para>vCenter Password</para></entry>
            <entry><para>Enter the password for the user named above.</para></entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry><para>vCenter Datacenter</para></entry>
            <entry><para>Enter the vCenter datacenter that the cluster is in. For example,
                &quot;clouddcVM&quot;.</para></entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry><para>Override Public Traffic</para></entry>
            <entry><para>Enable this option to override the zone-wide public traffic for the cluster
                you are creating. </para></entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry><para>Public Traffic vSwitch Type</para></entry>
            <entry><para>This option is displayed only if you enable the Override Public Traffic
                option. Select VMware vNetwork Distributed Virtual Switch. </para>
              <para>If the vmware.use.dvswitch global parameter is true, the default option will be
                VMware vNetwork Distributed Virtual Switch.</para></entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry><para>Public Traffic vSwitch Name</para></entry>
            <entry><para>Name of virtual switch to be used for the public traffic.</para></entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry><para>Override Guest Traffic</para></entry>
            <entry><para>Enable the option to override the zone-wide guest traffic for the cluster
                you are creating.</para></entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry><para>Guest Traffic vSwitch Type</para></entry>
            <entry><para>This option is displayed only if you enable the Override Guest Traffic
                option. Select VMware vNetwork Distributed Virtual Switch. </para>
              <para>If the vmware.use.dvswitch global parameter is true, the default option will be
                VMware vNetwork Distributed Virtual Switch.</para></entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry><para>Guest Traffic vSwitch Name</para></entry>
            <entry><para>Name of virtual switch to be used for guest traffic.</para></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
  </section>
</section>
