<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "cloudstack.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<!-- Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
    or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
    distributed with this work for additional information
    regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
    to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
    "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
    with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
    software distributed under the License is distributed on an
    "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
    KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
    specific language governing permissions and limitations
    under the License.
-->
<section id="vpc">
  <title>About Virtual Private Clouds</title>
  <para>&PRODUCT; Virtual Private Cloud is a private, isolated part of &PRODUCT;. A VPC can have its
    own virtual network topology that resembles a traditional physical network. You can launch VMs
    in the virtual network that can have private addresses in the range of your choice, for example:
    10.0.0.0/16. You can define network tiers within your VPC network range, which in turn enables
    you to group similar kinds of instances based on IP address range.</para>
  <para>For example, if a VPC has the private range 10.0.0.0/16, its guest networks can have the
    network ranges 10.0.1.0/24, 10.0.2.0/24, 10.0.3.0/24, and so on.</para>
  <formalpara>
    <title>Major Components of a VPC:</title>
    <para>A VPC is comprised of the following network components:</para>
  </formalpara>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">VPC</emphasis>: A VPC acts as a container for multiple isolated
        networks that can communicate with each other via its virtual router.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">Network Tiers</emphasis>: Each tier acts as an isolated network
        with its own VLANs and CIDR list, where you can place groups of resources, such as VMs. The
        tiers are segmented by means of VLANs. The NIC of each tier acts as its gateway.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">Virtual Router</emphasis>: A virtual router is automatically
        created and started when you create a VPC. The virtual router connect the tiers and direct
        traffic among the public gateway, the VPN gateways, and the NAT instances. For each tier, a
        corresponding NIC and IP exist in the virtual router. The virtual router provides DNS and
        DHCP services through its IP.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">Public Gateway</emphasis>: The traffic to and from the Internet
        routed to the VPC through the public gateway. In a VPC, the public gateway is not exposed to
        the end user; therefore, static routes are not support for the public gateway.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">Private Gateway</emphasis>: All the traffic to and from a private
        network routed to the VPC through the private gateway. For more information, see <xref
          linkend="add-gateway-vpc"/>.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">VPN Gateway</emphasis>: The VPC side of a VPN connection.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">Site-to-Site VPN Connection</emphasis>: A hardware-based VPN
        connection between your VPC and your datacenter, home network, or co-location facility. For
        more information, see <xref linkend="site-to-site-vpn"/>.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">Customer Gateway</emphasis>: The customer side of a VPN
        Connection. For more information, see <xref linkend="create-vpn-customer-gateway"/>.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">NAT Instance</emphasis>: An instance that provides Port Address
        Translation for instances to access the Internet via the public gateway. For more
        information, see <xref linkend="enable-disable-static-nat-vpc"/>.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">Network ACL</emphasis>:  Network ACL is a group of Network ACL
        items. Network ACL items are nothing but numbered rules that are evaluated in order,
        starting with the lowest numbered rule. These rules determine whether traffic is allowed in
        or out of any tier associated with the network ACL. For more information, see <xref linkend="configure-acl"/>.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <formalpara>
    <title>Network Architecture in a VPC</title>
    <para>In a VPC, the following four basic options of network architectures are present:</para>
  </formalpara>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>VPC with a public gateway only</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>VPC with public and private gateways</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>VPC with public and private gateways and site-to-site VPN access</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>VPC with a private gateway only and site-to-site VPN access</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <formalpara>
    <title>Connectivity Options for a VPC</title>
    <para>You can connect your VPC to:</para>
  </formalpara>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>The Internet through the public gateway.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>The corporate datacenter by using a site-to-site VPN connection through the VPN
        gateway.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Both the Internet and your corporate datacenter by using both the public gateway and a
        VPN gateway.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <formalpara>
    <title>VPC Network Considerations</title>
    <para>Consider the following before you create a VPC:</para>
  </formalpara>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>A VPC, by default, is created in the enabled state.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>A VPC can be created in Advance zone only, and can't belong to more than one zone at a
        time.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>The default number of VPCs an account can create is 20. However, you can change it by
        using the max.account.vpcs global parameter, which controls the maximum number of VPCs an
        account is allowed to create.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>The default number of tiers an account can create within a VPC is 3. You can configure
        this number by using the vpc.max.networks parameter.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Each tier should have an unique CIDR in the VPC. Ensure that the tier's CIDR should be
        within the VPC CIDR range.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>A tier belongs to only one VPC. </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>All network tiers inside the VPC should belong to the same account.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>When a VPC is created, by default, a SourceNAT IP is allocated to it. The Source NAT IP
        is released only when the VPC is removed.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>A public IP can be used for only one purpose at a time. If the IP is a sourceNAT, it
        cannot be used for StaticNAT or port forwarding.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>The instances can only have a private IP address that you provision. To communicate with
        the Internet, enable NAT to an instance that you launch in your VPC.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Only new networks can be added to a VPC. The maximum number of networks per VPC is
        limited by the value you specify in the vpc.max.networks parameter. The default value is
        three.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>The load balancing service can be supported by only one tier inside the VPC.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>If an IP address is assigned to a tier:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>That IP can't be used by more than one tier at a time in the VPC. For example, if
            you have tiers A and B, and a public IP1, you can create a port forwarding rule by using
            the IP either for A or B, but not for both.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>That IP can't be used for StaticNAT, load balancing, or port forwarding rules for
            another guest network inside the VPC.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Remote access VPN is not supported in VPC networks.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
</section>
